<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Believers-baptism from heaven, and of divine institution Infants-baptism from earth, and human invention. Proved from the commission of Christ, the great law-giver to the gospel-church. With a brief, yet sufficient answer to Thomas Wall's book, called, Baptism anatomized. Together with a brief answer to a part of Mr. Daniel William's catechism, in his book unto youth. By Hercules Collins, a servant of the servants of Christ.</title>
            <author>Collins, Hercules, d. 1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B20542</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5360</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224066</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834641</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834641</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154397</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B20542)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154397)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1809:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Believers-baptism from heaven, and of divine institution Infants-baptism from earth, and human invention. Proved from the commission of Christ, the great law-giver to the gospel-church. With a brief, yet sufficient answer to Thomas Wall's book, called, Baptism anatomized. Together with a brief answer to a part of Mr. Daniel William's catechism, in his book unto youth. By Hercules Collins, a servant of the servants of Christ.</title>
                  <author>Collins, Hercules, d. 1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 139, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author, and sold by J. Hancock, in Castle-Alley near the Royal-Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With errata on final page of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Congregational Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wall, Thomas --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Williams, Daniel, 1643?-1716 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154397:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154397:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154397:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Believers-Baptiſm from Heaven,</hi> and of Divine Inſtitution. <hi>Infants-Baptiſm from Earth,</hi> and Human Invention.</p>
            <p>Proved from the Commiſſion of Chriſt, the great Law-giver to the Goſpel-Church.</p>
            <p>With a Brief, yet ſufficient Anſwer to <hi>Thomas Wall</hi>'s Book, called, <hi>Baptiſm Anatomized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with a brief Anſwer to a part of Mr. <hi>Daniel Williams</hi>'s Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm, in his Book unto Youth.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Hercules Collins,</hi> a Servant of the Servants of Chriſt.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luke 7.29, 30.</hi>
               </bibl> — And the Publicans juſtified God, being baptized with the Baptiſm of <hi>John.</hi> But the Phariſees, and the Expounders of the Law, rejected the Counſel of God againſt themſelves, in not being baptized with the Baptiſm of <hi>John.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for the Author, and ſold by <hi>J. Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock,</hi> in Caſtle-Alley near the <hi>Royal-Exchange,</hi> 1691.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:154397:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:154397:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:154397:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154397:4"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHap. 1.</hi> An Introduction, <hi>Page 5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 2.</hi> Contains the Doctrines, <hi>Page 8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 3.</hi> That Baptiſm is Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, <hi>Page 11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 4.</hi> Shewing Believers only are the proper Subjects of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, <hi>Page 20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 5.</hi> Anſwer to Objections, <hi>Page 27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 6.</hi> Natural Inferences, <hi>Page 63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 7.</hi> Arecital of thoſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſpeaking of Baptiſm, <hi>Page 72</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 8.</hi> Of great Sufferings undergone, for maintaining
<pb facs="tcp:154397:5"/> Believers, and denying In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants-Baptiſm, <hi>Page 76</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 9.</hi> The Book epitomized, in comparing Believers-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm and Infant-Baptiſm to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, <hi>Page 81</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 10.</hi> The Miſcarriage of the German Anabaptists, <hi>(falſly ſo called)</hi> examined, and the Reproach from thence reflected upon that way, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, <hi>Page 95</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 11.</hi> A brief, but ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Anſwer to <hi>Tho. Wall</hi>'s Book, called <hi>Baptiſm Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miz'd, Page 108</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 12.</hi> A brief Anſwer to a part of Mr. <hi>D. Williams</hi> his Catechiſm, in his Book unto Youth, <hi>Page 128</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>In Page 108, 114, 115. for <hi>John Wall,</hi> read <hi>Thomas Wall.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface_to_the_reader">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:154397:5"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MY deſire is, that <hi>Thou</hi> would'ſt ſpend one Hour or Two ſeriouſly to read this ſmall Book; firſt of all beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of God it may be ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified to thy Soul. Read it without <hi>prejudice</hi> or <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality;</hi> and as one that is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to receive the Truth, and entring into another World, be like the Noble
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154397:6"/> 
               <hi>Bereans, ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to ſee whether theſe Things be ſo or no:</hi> Take nothing from Man, tho never ſo Learned and Holy, upon truſt, without trial. With what confidence may a Man die when he hath, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> for his Faith and Practice? This is all from him that wiſheth your Soul's welfare,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:154397:6"/>
            <head>Water-Baptiſm Diſcours'd,</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>From St.<hi> Mark </hi>16.16. </bibl>
                  <hi>He that believeth, and is baptized, ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>IT was <hi>God's Command unto the Prophet</hi> Ezekiel,<note place="margin">Ezek. 43.11.</note> 
                  <hi>to ſhew</hi> his People <hi>the Form of his Houſe, with the goings in thereof,</hi> &amp;c. Know therefore, ye Servants of the Lord, as Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion was the Door into the Jewiſh Church, which was Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional; ſo Baptiſm is the Door
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154397:7"/> into the Goſpel-Church, which is Congregational. Hence St. <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith, <hi>They that gladly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Apoſtles Words, were baptized, and added unto the Church in number about three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Souls,</hi> Acts 2.41.</p>
               <p>The Ancients call Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,<note n="*" place="margin">Janua Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentorum.
<q>
                        <p>As Liſting is the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn engaging Sign in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Army, ſo is Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm into the Church.</p>
                        <bibl>Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Baptiſm is a ſign of entring into the Church.</p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Urſinus.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Baptiſm is the ſolemn admiſſion of the Party into the viſible Church.</p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Aſſemb. Catechiſm.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </q>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>the Gate of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments,</hi> becauſe by it <hi>we enter into the Church,</hi> and have Communion with Saints.</p>
               <p>In the Jewiſh Church they became Members, as they were the fleſhly, or natural Seed of <hi>Abraham;</hi> but now Members of the Goſpel-Church, as the ſpiritual Seed of <hi>Abraham.</hi> Now we muſt not reckon <hi>from</hi> Abraham <hi>unto Chriſt, but from Chriſt to</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham: <hi>If we are Chriſt's, then are we</hi> Abraham<hi>'s Seed,</hi> Gal. 3.29. not Chriſt's becauſe we are <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi>'s, or our Parents Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers.</p>
               <p>Under the Old Teſtament, Perſons became Members of the Church by Generation; under
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:154397:7"/> the New by Regeneration,<note place="margin">Baptiſm is a Foundation-Principle of Church-Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, <hi>Heb. 6.1, 2.</hi> But the Foundation-Principle of Salvation, is Faith in Chriſt.</note> 
                  <hi>or at leaſt a Profeſſion of it.</hi> Hence we read, <hi>Perſons were first Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then Baptized, after added unto the Church,</hi> Acts 2.41.</p>
               <p>My Intent is, to diſplay this Sacrament in its <hi>Apoſtolick Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Purity,</hi> free from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterations of Men, a Sin which God charged upon the Learned Jews, that they made void the Commands of God by their Traditions. O that none of the Learned among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, eſpecially thoſe of the Reformed Churches, may be chargeable with ſetting up Mens Inventions in the room of Chriſt's Inſtitutions.<note place="margin">Mat. 15.6, 9.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:154397:8"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>THis Text, <hi>He that believeth, and is Baptized,</hi> is a great part of the Commiſſion, which is the Foundation and Warrant for all Goſpel-Miniſters Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Baptizing unto the end of the World.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>☞ Obedience is to be grounded upon the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of the Commander, not the Judgment of the Subject.</p>
                     <p>The Architect was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded with a bundle of Rods, for bringing, as he thought, a fitter piece of Timber than was commanded by the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Conſul.</p>
                     <p>And it coſt a Roman Gentleman his Life, his own Father being Judg, tho conquering an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, being done contrary to his General's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. Remember <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note>It's worth our noting;</p>
               <p>Here is firſt <hi>Faith,</hi> then <hi>Baptiſm.</hi> Therefore to baptize before there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny appearance of Faith, is directly contrary unto this unerring ſtanding Rule, and doth reflect upon our Lord and Lawgiver, as if he ſpoke raſhly and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderately, putting that firſt which ſhould be laſt, and <hi>that laſt</hi> which ſhould <hi>be first.</hi> And ſo in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel Text, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18. there is <hi>first Teaching</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>baptizing,</hi> not firſt <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized,</hi> but <hi>taught</hi> firſt.</p>
               <p>From this part of our Lord's Commiſſion, we collect theſe Truths.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:154397:8"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 1. It's the unalterable Will of Jeſus Chriſt, who is King and Law-giver to his Goſpel-Church, that all Perſons believe before they are baptized.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 2. It's the indiſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Duty of all true Believers to be Baptized.</p>
               <p>I call it an indiſpenſable Duty, becauſe I know no Place where our Lord hath left this to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Believers to do it, or leave it undone, as beſt pleaſeth them.</p>
               <p>Therefore if this be your Lord and Saviour's Will, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers,</hi> pray obey him. In your Prayers you deſire you may be enabled to do his Will on Earth as it is in Heaven: This is one part of his Divine Will; Your Redeemer was willing to be <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in Blood</hi> for your Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and will not you be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in Water, in obedience to his Commiſſion? Moreover, Chriſt calls it,<note place="margin">Mat. 3.15.</note> a <hi>fulfilling of all Righteouſneſs.</hi> I am perſwaded, ſhould God have commanded
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:154397:9"/> 
                  <hi>ſome great Thing,</hi> as was once ſaid to <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Kings 5.13.</note> it would have been done by many in the Reformed Churches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now: How much rather, when he only ſaith, <hi>Go, waſh and be clean?</hi> Or, as <hi>Ananias</hi> unto St. <hi>Paul, Ariſe, and waſh away thy Sins,</hi> viz. <hi>Sacramentally and Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolically,</hi> as it is in the Lord's Supper. Take heed, my Friends, you are not guilty of Contempt, looking upon Chriſt's Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as mean low and little things; for nothing is mean that hath Chriſt's Authority ſtamp'd upon it, tho it were the blowing of Rams-horns round the Walls of <hi>Jericho:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joſh. 6.13.</note>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 20.24, 25.</note> Making an Altar of Earth, or rough Stone; taking the Blood of the Treſpaſs-Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, putting it on the Lap of the High-Prieſt's right Ear,<note place="margin">Levit. 8.24.</note> the Thumb of the right Hand, the great Toe of the right Foot, having on it a Divine Stamp, is an Argument ſufficient for our Obedience.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 9.18.</note>St. <hi>Paul,</hi> a very learned Man; the Eunuch who was Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:154397:9"/> under <hi>Candace</hi> Queen of <hi>Ethiopia, Criſpus</hi> a chief Ruler, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius</hi> great Emperors, our Lord, the only Potentate, accounted it ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable a thing, as to practiſe it, when about thirty Years of Age, and led us the way, as well by his Example as Commiſſion. Nothing ſure can be more obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Believers unto Obedience, than their Saviour's Precept and Precedent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> What Baptiſm is.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, <hi>Negatively;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Not <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Mat. 28.18, 19, 20.</note> It's not ſprinkling, dropping, or pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Water. Sprinkling is known to be Rantiſing, not Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing, or Baptiſm. Baptiſm is an external waſhing, plunging or dipping a profeſt Believer, in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:154397:10"/>
               <p>Which I thus demonſtrate.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The Hebrew word</hi> Tabal, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Dip. <hi>The Septuagint tranſlate it</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>as Dr.</hi> Hammond <hi>notes on</hi> John 13.10. Gen. 37.31. Levit. 4.6. Deut. 33.24. 2 Kings 5.14. Joſh. 3.15.</note>1. From the Scripture-accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Word; the word <hi>Baptize</hi> in the New Teſtament, is taken from the word <hi>Dip</hi> in the Old, as the Learned do know: Where 'tis ſaid, Joſeph<hi>'s Coat was dipt in Blood. The Prieſt's Finger dipt in Blood.</hi> Aſher<hi>'s Foot dipt in Oil. The Prieſts Feet dipt in</hi> Jordan. Naaman <hi>waſh'd or dipt ſeven times in the ſame River;</hi> with many more places of Scripture.<note place="margin">☞</note> Moreover, 'tis worth our noting, the word tranſlated <hi>Dip,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 13.26. Rev. 19.13. Luke 16.24.</note> concerning the <hi>Sop Judas had:</hi> And where it's ſaid, <hi>Chriſt's Veſture was dipt in Blood,</hi> it is from the ſame Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal word <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is, that our Tranſlators might (had they pleaſed) have rendred the word <hi>Baptizing, Dipping,</hi> being from the ſame Theme <hi>Bapto,</hi> as <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi> is.</p>
               <p>We are much to be governed by the <hi>Common and Vulgar</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation of words, as they were uſed and underſtood among all Nations. God ſo inſpired the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154397:10"/> Prophets and Apoſtles, to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his Mind always in ſuch words, as were underſtood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the vulgar and ordinary People, or elſe they would have been <hi>Barbarians</hi> unto them. We cannot underſtand each other in Diſcourſe, but this way; I call for a Book, it's readily given me, becauſe every one knows what it is we call a Book: So if <hi>Tabal</hi> were uſed among the <hi>Hebrews</hi> for <hi>Dip,</hi> in the common Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; and the Learned <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> by the Order of <hi>Ptolomy</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> did tranſlate that word <hi>Baptizo,</hi> which was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly accepted for <hi>Dip</hi> among the <hi>Grecians;</hi> and we alſo tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate <hi>Baptizo, Dip;</hi> none but an <hi>Enthuſiaſt</hi> will object againſt the common acceptation of words.</p>
               <p>This puts me in mind of a Diſcourſe between Biſhop <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hanſerd Knowllys,</hi> about the Propriety of the word <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizo;</hi> the Biſhop ſaid it ſignified to <hi>ſprinkle</hi> as well as <hi>dip.</hi> Mr. <hi>Knowllys</hi> ſaid, it ſignified only to <hi>dip,</hi> there being other words
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:154397:11"/> in the Greek for <hi>ſprinkling</hi> and <hi>pouring.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">'Tis obſervable, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> to waſh, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> to pour, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> to ſprinkle, are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver taken or uſed for Dip or Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize; nor <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſimply ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for Waſhing, by ſprinkling or pouring. <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers</hi> on Baptiſm, <hi>p. 206.</hi>
                  </note> To end this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy, thoſe who could produce the beſt and moſt Authors for their Senſe, ſhould carry it: the Biſhop, after ſome ſearch, found Two for his Opinion; Mr. <hi>Knowllys</hi> brings Seventy for his Two, namely, the <hi>Septuagint;</hi> and ſo the Controverſy ended.</p>
               <p>The Writings of the moſt Learned of the contrary Mind, do confeſs, that the Original Word<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> from whence <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is taken, ſignifieth properly <hi>to dip. Leigh's Critica Sacra,</hi> ſaith, <hi>The native ſignification of the Word, is,</hi> to dip into, <hi>or</hi> plunge un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Water, <hi>as the Dyer dips his Cloth in his Fats.</hi> The Book of <hi>Canons</hi> ſaith, <hi>You ſhall dip,</hi> &amp;c. So the <hi>Dutch</hi> tranſlate the Word, <hi>In thoſe Days came</hi> John the Dipper;<note place="margin">Ende doc Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ghe Doope was quam hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterſtont van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Water.</note> 
                  <hi>and when Jeſus was dipt, he came out of the Water. Calvin</hi> ſaith, <hi>We ſee what Faſhion the Ancients had to Adminiſter Baptiſm, for they plunged the whole Body into Water.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:154397:11"/>2. The end of the Ordinance ſheweth <hi>Baptiſm</hi> to be <hi>dipping;</hi> which is to hold forth unto a Believer, <hi>the Death, Burial, and Reſurrection of Chriſt;</hi> as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. <hi>We are buried with him in Baptiſm.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there be no manner of <hi>ſimilitude</hi> and <hi>likeneſs</hi> between Chriſt's Death and Burial, with <hi>ſprinkling a little Water on the Face,</hi> yet burying in the Water is as lively a Similitude and Likeneſs of Jeſus Chriſt's Death, as the breaking Bread, and pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the Wine is at the Lord's Table: So that they loſe one great End of this Ordinance, who Rantize inſtead of Baptize; for no Man accounts him buried, who hath only Earth caſt on his Face, but he who is in the Heart of the Earth, and covered with the ſame.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>John</hi> the beloved Diſciple, gives this as the Reaſon why <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> baptized in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 3.23.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe there was much Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter there,</hi> the place was commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious for that Ordinance: Hence
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:154397:12"/> our bleſſed Saviour came from <hi>Galilee</hi> to <hi>Jordan,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">From <hi>Galilee</hi> to <hi>Jordan,</hi> where <hi>John</hi> baptized, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thirty or forty miles.</note> 
                  <hi>to be baptized of him there;</hi> which if Sprinkling would have done, there had been no need of much Water nor Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is <hi>Dipping,</hi> appears from Scripture-Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phors explaining it:<note place="margin">Luke 15.50.</note> 
                  <hi>Our Lord's Sufferings are called a Baptiſm,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>his Pains</hi> were not only up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one part of his Body,<note place="margin">No ſuch thing as Sprinkling or Rantizing uſed in the Apoſtles Days, nor many Ages after. <hi>Mede</hi>'s Diatri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be.</note> but his <hi>whole Soul and Body</hi> was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized and plunged into Sorrows. Thus one that is Baptized, is plunged under Water, to ſhew how Chriſt was Baptized and plunged into Sorrows for Man's ſake. <hi>Great Meaſures of the Spirit</hi> are alſo diſcovered, by Perſons being ſaid to be <hi>Baptized with the Spirit;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 1.5.</note> for where the word <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi> is uſed, whether it be <hi>join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Suffering, with the Spirit, or with Water,</hi> it always holds forth a great quantity, <hi>either of Sufferings, of the Spirit, or Water.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Hence in the 5th place, The vaſt height of Waters <hi>which ſtood above the Church in the Red
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:154397:12"/> Sea,</hi> like a high Wall, is called,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>A Baptiſm unto</hi> Moſes, <hi>in the Cloud, and in the Sea,</hi> becauſe encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed with it; for the Ordinance of Baptiſm was not then in force; but Circumciſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot be meant God's Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Baptiſm, but ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the great Care God had of his Church, that as he fed them miraculouſly, and gave them Water out of a Rock in the Wilderneſs;<note place="margin">Baptiſm ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth properly plunging in Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or waſhing by dipping. Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s Rule of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> ſo he did not leave them in the Red Sea, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſs'd them about by his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence, with Water and the Cloud, as Perſons are encompaſſed with that Element when Baptized.</p>
               <p>Hence in the 6th place. Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is explained by the <hi>Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor of a Garment;</hi> which the Apoſtle refers unto, when he calls <hi>Baptiſm, a putting on Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 3.27.</note> As the Servant, by his Lord's Livery, declares whoſe he is; ſo the long white Robe of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm ſheweth us to be <hi>the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Lord Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:154397:13"/>(7.) <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is not only cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>a Waſhing, by</hi> Ananias <hi>and</hi> Peter, (<hi>Acts</hi> 22.16. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5.) <hi>but the waſhing of the Soul in Regeneration, is held forth in this Symbol and Sign,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auſtin</hi> and <hi>Paulinus,</hi> in the 7th Century, in <hi>England,</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized great Multitudes in the River <hi>Trent</hi> and <hi>Swale.</hi> Hence, ſaith Mr. <hi>Fox,</hi> there was no uſe of Fonts then. <hi>Fox</hi>'s Acts and Monuments, <hi>9 Edit. Vol. 1. p. 132.</hi>
                  </note> by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, when he ſpeaks of the waſhing of Regeneration</hi> unto <hi>Titus.</hi> Now we know, every Faculty of the Soul is waſhed in the Blood of Chriſt; and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Faculty ſanctified by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, not a part of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, but all the Faculties; therefore wiſely ſet forth by Baptiſm, wherein not only <hi>a part, but the whole</hi> Body is waſh'd and cleanſed in Water.</p>
               <p n="8">(8.) This is further cleared from the practice of the moſt <hi>pure Apoſtolick Times.</hi> 'Tis ſaid of our moſt bleſſed Lord Jeſus, <hi>That he went up out of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 3.15, 16, 17.</note> which in common ſenſe ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies, He firſt went down, not only to the Water, but <hi>into</hi> the Water, <hi>and came up out of the Water.</hi> Of <hi>Philip</hi> and the <hi>Eunuch</hi> 'tis ſaid,<note place="margin">Acts 8.36, 40.</note> 
                  <hi>They went down both, not only to the Water, but into the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:154397:13"/> Water, and came up out of the Water:</hi> if Sprinkling would have done, they need only go to and come from it; but they knew the Commiſſion could not be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, unleſs they went down into the Water.<note place="margin">The Miniſter is to dip in Water, as the meeteſt Act, the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> notes it. <hi>Rogers</hi> on the Sacrament.</note> Thus you ſee the Places where the Apoſtles Baptized, were in Rivers, and where was much Water: You ſee their Act and Poſture, they went down into the Water; you ſee their End was, to exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit and ſhew forth Chriſt's Death, Burial, and Reſurecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>If any ſhould ask, <hi>Why Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling will not do as well as Dipping?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, (1.) Becauſe <hi>that is another thing</hi> than Chriſt hath commanded; and 'tis high pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption to <hi>change God's Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 24.5.</note> Tho there was no more virtue in the <hi>Waters of</hi> Jordan, <hi>than of</hi> Damaſcus; yet <hi>Naaman</hi> muſt keep to God's Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. (2.) In ſo doing, we loſe the End of the <hi>Ordinance,</hi> which as aforeſaid, is to ſhew forth the Death and Reſurrection of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:154397:14"/> Chriſt. (3.) We muſt keep the Ordinances as they were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered unto us;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.2.</note>
                  <note place="margin">'Tis a known Maxim, to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe any thing in the Worſhip of God, as an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of his, without an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, ought to be eſteemed Will-worſhip &amp; Idolatry. And that there is a neceſſity for Scripture-Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant every Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in Divine Worſhip, is owned by <hi>Luther, Auſtin, Calvin, Baſil, Theoph. Tertul,</hi> Mr. <hi>Ball;</hi> and in the 6th Article of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> alſo <hi>Bellarmine.</hi>
                  </note> as <hi>Moſes</hi> was to make all things according to the Pattern ſhewed him in the Mount. (4.) God is a Jealous God, and ſtands upon ſmall things in Matters of Worſhip: Had <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> but lifted up a Tool upon the Altar of ruff Stone to beautify it, they would have polluted it, becauſe contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Command. (5.) This hath no likeneſs to the holy Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Shewing that profeſſing Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, and them only, are the proper Subjects of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</head>
               <p>Which I demonſtrate;</p>
               <p>FIrſt, From Goſpel-Precept: Our Text ſaith, <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:154397:14"/> and is baptized.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſaith, 'Tis no where in the Apoſtles Writings Infants were baptized.</note> The pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel Text, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. is worthy of conſideration by way of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. The Commiſſion is, <hi>Go;</hi> the Subjects ſpoken to, are, <hi>his Apoſtles;</hi> the Matter of it is, <hi>to teach, and baptize;</hi> the Extent of it is, <hi>into all the World, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in hot Countries, but in Cold.</hi> The Order in this Commiſſion is, firſt <hi>to teach,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> then after taught and diſcipellized, <hi>to baptize</hi> them. Therefore to baptize them,<note place="margin">We meet with no Example in Scripture for baptizing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants. <hi>Magd.</hi> Hiſt. Cent. <hi>1. L. 2. p. 196.</hi>
                  </note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore taught, is quite contrary to the Command. The words of Inſtitution, in whoſe Name it is to be done, is the glorious Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, <hi>in the Name of Father, Son, and Holy Spirit;</hi> this muſt be ſome great thing which is done by ſo great Authority. Unto this is annexed a glorious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Divine Preſence, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the End of that Age, but the End of the World<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>; and to put us out of all doubt about it, 'tis back'd with an Aſſeveration, <hi>Amen,</hi> ſo it ſhall be. Finally, here is a Note of Obſervation, <hi>[Lo]</hi> our Lord would not have ſo
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:154397:15"/> great a Commiſſion and Promiſe diſregarded; therefore ſaith he, <hi>Lo,</hi> that is, obſerve what I have ſaid: wherever you find the word <hi>Lo, Mark,</hi> or <hi>Behold,</hi> you will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways find ſomething very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable it relates unto in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text. Now in purſuance of this Commiſſion, <hi>Peter</hi> exhorted the Murderers of Chriſt, when they were convicted, and cried out, <hi>What ſhall we do?</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Repent, and be baptized, every one of you, in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt, for the Remiſſion of Sins, and ye ſhall receive the Gift of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2ly, This appears from Goſpel-Precedent and Example; the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles in purſuance of their Commiſſion, baptize none elſe but ſuch. Hence <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> tells the <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Sadduces</hi> which came to his Baptiſm,<note place="margin">As <hi>Iſaac</hi> was brought forth by the Word of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, ſo muſt we be born of the Word of God, which only makes Baptiſm powerful and effectual. <hi>Magd.</hi> Cent. <hi>5.</hi> p. <hi>363.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>they muſt first bring forth Fruit meet for, or to amendment of Life,</hi> and not to think the old Argument for Circumciſion, [that <hi>Abraham</hi> was their Father] would give them a right to Goſpel-Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances. It's not the Faith of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:154397:15"/> Parents gives Children a right to the Seals of the New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, but a perſonal Faith; hence <hi>Philip</hi> would not baptize the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> but upon profeſſion of Faith. In a word, all the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Churches were conſtituted and planted upon this Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on-Principle,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.1, 2. Acts 2.41. Chap. 8.12. Chap. 16.14. Coloſſ. 2.10. Acts 18.8. Rom. 6.4. Gal. 3.26. Acts 19.1, 2, 3. Epheſ. 4.4.</note> as theſe Scriptures ſhow in the Margent, <hi>viz.</hi> the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem, Samaria, Ceſaria, Philippi, Coloſs, Corinth, Rome, Galatia, Epheſus,</hi> &amp;c. To conclude, If the Churches of Chriſt were ſo planted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted in the Primitive Times, they ought to be ſo ſtill, unleſs any can ſhew where Chriſt hath ſince that altered the Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Churches.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly, This Ordinance cannot concern Infants, but Believers; becauſe it's a teſtification of the Remiſſion of Sins, and Salvation, to the <hi>worthy Receiver and Subject of it;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 2.38. Mark 16.16.</note> elſe why doth <hi>Peter</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe <hi>remiſſion of Sin, and the Gift of the Holy Ghoſt</hi> to ſuch? And why did our Lord join <hi>Faith, Baptiſm, and Salvation</hi> all in one
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:154397:16"/> Verſe,<note place="margin">Baptiſm is never enjoined as a Means of Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Sins and Eternal Life, but ſomething of Duty, Choice, and Sanctity, is join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it, in order to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of the End ſo mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Dr. <hi>Taylor.</hi>
                  </note> but that the Ordinance ſhould be a Pledg to the Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of thoſe great things? We collect as much from <hi>Acts</hi> 22.16. where <hi>Ananias</hi> exhorted <hi>Paul, to ariſe, and be baptized, and waſh away his Sins;</hi> that is, put that Duty in practice which will be a <hi>Confirmation of thy Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> ſo we underſtand <hi>Peter,</hi> The like Figure, <hi>whereunto Baptiſm doth now ſave us, viz.</hi> As the Ark was the inſtrumental way of God's ſaving <hi>Noah</hi> by his Grace,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1 Pet. 3.20.</hi> Baptiſm is our Marriage-Ring, Military Preſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafting into Chriſt, our Badg and Cognizance, our Ship, our Ark, our Red-Sea, our putting on Chriſt. <hi>Dan. Rogers.</hi>
                  </note> ſo Faith in Chriſt's Death and Reſurrection, is the way God ſaves our Souls, this being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed unto us in the Figure of Baptiſm, as well as at the Lord's Table. But what have Infants to do with this, who are not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to take in the Comfort exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited and held forth in it? <hi>This is Meat for ſtrong Men, not Babes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4ly, Believers only muſt be the Subjects of this Ordinance, becauſe it holds forth a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant the Subject <hi>makes actually with God.</hi> Hence ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3. <hi>Know you not, as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:154397:16"/> many as were baptized into Chriſt, were baptized into his Death?</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, In that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance <hi>you did covenant and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to die unto Sin, and live a new Life; Therefore,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>how can you that are dead to Sin, live any longer therein?</hi> And this you have profeſs'd in your Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, as in the words of the Inſtitution,<note place="margin">Goſſops and Sureties are no where found in Holy Scripture, but in the Pope's Decree, and Common-Prayer Book. Which the Parliament in K. <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th's time, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, There was no other diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between that and the Maſs-Book, only a few things left out, but that one was in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, the other in Engliſh. <hi>Fox</hi>'s Acts &amp; Mon. <hi>Edit. 9. Vol. 2. Book 9. p. 14, 15.</hi>
                  </note> the whole Trinity gives it ſelf unto the Believer: So he dedicates himſelf volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily to the Service of the whole Trinity, <hi>Father, Son, and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> In all Covenants of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, there is required, <hi>the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the Judgment, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Will, it muſt be an Act of Choice:</hi> As the <hi>Eunuch</hi> ſaid, <hi>See, here is Water, what hinders me to be baptized?</hi> But none of theſe things are agreeable to an Infant: and as they are not able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into Covenant themſelves, if others do it for them, 'tis not only Unſcriptural, but Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptural. Can Perſons cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to keep others from Sin, when they find it too hard a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:154397:17"/> work to keep themſelves?</p>
               <p n="5">5ly, Baptiſm is a lively repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of Regeneration, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can only <hi>affect Believers.</hi> The Apoſtle alludes unto Baptiſm, when he ſpeaks of <hi>the waſhing of Regeneration,</hi> Titus 3.5. His meaning is, that the Ordinance is a lively Badg, Symbol, and Sign of Regeneration, and the New Birth. The Apoſtle to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> Ch. 2.12. tells them, <hi>That their Baptiſm did exhibit and ſhew forth their being dead,</hi> and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen with Chriſt through that Faith, which was of that <hi>Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent Operation, which raiſed Chriſt from the Dead;</hi> but no Signs of Regeneration appear in Infants at Baptiſm: that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truly ſaid,<note place="margin">Saith the Papiſt to the Prelat, You prove that Sacraments convey Grace in the very Act, as we aſſert; for juſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Baptiſm, the Child was an Heir of Hell, and Child of Wrath, but being baptized, it is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated and born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, as your Common-Prayer Book ſaith.</note> in the <hi>Common-Prayer Book,</hi> after the Child is ſprinkled, <hi>Foraſmuch as this Child is regenerated and born again,</hi> which juſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was acknowledged to be <hi>a Child of Wrath, and an Heir of Hell.</hi> We ſay, tho God hath promiſed his Preſence in all his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:154397:17"/> yet we alſo ſay, Perſons are not to be Baptized, that they may be Regenerated, but to hold forth and ſignify Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, therefore Baptiſm can no ways affect little Infants.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Contains the Anſwer of Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections.</head>
               <div n="1" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>Objection 1.</head>
                     <p>FEW Learned Men own this way of Baptizing, only a few mechanick poor illiterate Perſons.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>I Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Not many wiſe Men after the Fleſh are called,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.24, 29. Chriſt did not ordinarily make uſe of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Rabbies</hi> among the <hi>Jews</hi> to preach the Goſpel, but rather thoſe who were counted illite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and ignorant, that no Fleſh might glory in his Preſence: God gets the more praiſe by making
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:154397:18"/> uſe of <hi>Babes and Sucklings. Chriſt thanks the Father,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 8.2.</note> 
                        <hi>that Divine Things were hid from the Wiſe and Prudent, ſuch as the World ſo accounted,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 11.27.</note> 
                        <hi>and revealed unto Babes,</hi> becauſe they would render the Glory unto God, while the worldly <hi>wiſe Men</hi> would take it to themſelves. 2. Thoſe who have the moſt humane Litera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are no Rule, but God's Word: we muſt follow <hi>Paul</hi> no further than he follows Chriſt. 3. The Holy Scriptures account no Man truly Wiſe and Learned, but thoſe taught of God, and that keep his Commands, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.10. The Learned <hi>Phariſees,</hi> and Expounders of the Law, rejected the Counſel of God againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in not being Baptized. 4. Are there no Learned of this Practice? What think you of St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">See <hi>Danvers</hi> on Baptiſm, <hi>p. 60, 61, 62, 63.</hi> Many of thoſe born of Chriſtian Parents.</note> 
                        <hi>Baſil, Gregory Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anzen, Jerom, Ambroſe, Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, Conſtantine, Theodoſius, Paul,</hi> and as the Crown of all, our <hi>Lord Jeſus?</hi> were all theſe Illiterate and Ignorant?</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <div type="objection">
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:154397:18"/>
                     <head>Object. 2.</head>
                     <p>The Children of Believers are in the Covenant,<note place="margin">They ſay, the <hi>Foederati</hi> were to be the <hi>Signati.</hi>
                        </note> therefore ought to have the Seal of the Covenant, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>I Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>There is but two ways of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Covenant, <hi>Abſolutely,</hi> or <hi>Conditionally.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Let it firſt be proved, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Seed of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers are in Covenant; then, 2ly, if ſo, that they ought to be baptized. Female Children under the Law, had a legal or federal Holineſs, yet not to be Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed.</note> No Believer dare ſay, all his Infant-Seed are in the Covenant of Grace <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely,</hi> for then they muſt all be ſaved; but we ſee <hi>Abraham</hi> had an <hi>Iſhmael, Iſaac</hi> an <hi>Eſau, David</hi> an <hi>Abſalom, Samuel</hi> Sons of <hi>Beli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,</hi> &amp;c. ſo that they cannot be baptized under that Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Or, 2. Perſons are in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace <hi>Conditionally, viz.</hi> in caſe they Believe and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. Now under this Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, the Children of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers have the ſame Intereſt in the Covenant, and Sign of the Covenant. <hi>And Children of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers have a right no other way, to the one or other; the promiſe of Remiſſion, and Gift of the Holy Ghoſt, is made, as well to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, which are afar off, as to the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:154397:19"/> natural Seed of</hi> Abraham, if they have the ſame Qualifications, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. <hi>albeit Heathens by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and theſe are oft-times made the Subjects of Grace, when <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers Children</hi> are left. Hence a wicked <hi>Ahaz,</hi> hath a good <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah;</hi> ungodly <hi>Abia,</hi> a good <hi>Aſa;</hi> wicked <hi>Ammon,</hi> a good <hi>Joſiah;</hi> idolatrous <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> a good <hi>Abijah.</hi> But were all the Children of Believers in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, it follows not that therefore they ought to be baptized, no more than they may come to the Lord's Supper, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they want the Qualification required in that Duty. And whereas it is further urged, from the 2d of the <hi>Acts,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The word Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren there, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Jews, and not particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly their Infant Children; my Child is my Child, tho <hi>40</hi> or <hi>50</hi> Years old.</note> 
                        <hi>the Promiſe is to you and your Children.</hi> The ſcope of that place ſeems to be this; When the <hi>Jews</hi> were pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked at their Heart <hi>for their Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying Chriſt,</hi> upon <hi>Peter</hi>'s Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, they cry out, <hi>Men and Brethren, what ſhall we do?</hi> The Apoſtle exhorts them what to do, <hi>viz. Repent, and be Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed;</hi> and for their Comfort ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joins,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:154397:19"/> that the Promiſe of <hi>Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Sins,</hi> alſo of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> was like to be their Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>and their Childrens alſo,</hi> if they did the ſame; tho they once called for Chriſt's Blood upon their Heads, and their Children, yet now if you and your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren believe in that Chriſt you have Crucified, thoſe Promiſes are to the one and to the other, yea, to all afar off, the poor <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles;</hi> for ſince the partition Wall is broken down, <hi>Jew, Greek,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Col. 3.11.</note> 
                        <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barian, Scythian, Bond, Free, Male, Female,</hi> all one by Faith in Chriſt; <hi>For we are all the Children of God by Faith in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Gal. 3.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 3.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Infant-Baptiſm neither hath Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept nor Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in God's Word, is confeſs'd by</hi> Luther Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, Zwingli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Melancthon, Bucer, Calvin, Chochler, Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus, Rogers, <hi>Mr.</hi> Baxter. Dauvers <hi>on Baptiſm,</hi> p. 90, 91.</note>
                     </head>
                     <p>The Infant-Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> was Circumciſed; therefore the Infant-Seed of Believers may be Baptized.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>I Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Abraham</hi> had a plain Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Command for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; Believers have none for the latter. In Matters of Worſhip, we muſt keep to the Inſtitution, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did to the Pattern
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:154397:20"/> ſhew'd him in the Mount. Tho <hi>Lot</hi> was a Believer, his Children were not to have the ſign of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, becauſe limited unto <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed and Family, alſo to ſuch a Sex, and ſuch a Day. So hath God limited Baptiſm to Penitent Believers;<note place="margin">Whoever practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes an Inſtitution otherwiſe than was appointed by the great Law-giver, does not honour the Ordinance, but an Idol of his own making.</note> therefore let us keep to the Inſtitution, and not be wiſe above what is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; and take not up with a dark Conſequence in the rejection of a plain Command, being not ſo ſatisfying to the true Reaſon of a Man, nor his Conſcience. Thoſe that argue for their Infant-Seeds Baptiſm from Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being entail'd unto <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Seed, may as well argue and ſay, the Prieſthood was by a Covenant entail'd on the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> and his Seed, therefore the Miniſtry is entail'd upon Goſpel-Preachers and their Seed: As this cannot be warranted, no more can the other.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 4.</head>
                     <p>Whole Families were Baptized: <hi>Ergo,</hi> Infants.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:154397:20"/>
                     <head>I Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>It's ſaid indeed, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.33.<note place="margin">Whereas ſome ſay, No doubt but the Jailor had Children. It may be very much queſtioned, ſeeing it hath been obſerved, ſome Years ago, that for very many Years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not one Child was born to the Jayl-keepers in all the County of <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>The Jaylor and all his were bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed;</hi> well they might, ſeeing they <hi>all believed,</hi> verſ. 34. <hi>So</hi> Criſpus <hi>the chief Ruler believed in God, with all his Houſe,</hi> Act. 18.8. <hi>And many of the</hi> Corinthians <hi>hearing, believed, and were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized. And for</hi> Lydia <hi>and her Houſhold, thoſe they Baptized, thoſe they comforted,</hi> ver. 40. But Infants could not take in that, nor the comfort of that <hi>ſpiritual Appellation or Relation of Brethren,</hi> as the Apoſtle calls them in <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi>'s Houſhold.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The word <hi>[all]</hi> doth not always <hi>intend every Individual</hi> in a Family. In 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.21. 'tis ſaid, Elkanah <hi>and all his Houſe went up to the yearly Sacrifice to</hi> Jeruſalem. Yet in the 22d it is ſaid, Hannah <hi>and the Child</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel <hi>ſtay'd at Home.</hi> So <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus Ceſar</hi> is ſaid to <hi>Tax all the Word,</hi> Luke 2.1. <hi>which was no more of the World, than that little part where the Roman Empire ſtretched.</hi> Should there be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:154397:21"/> in any of theſe Families,<note place="margin">To carry a poor ignorant Infant to the Ordinance of Baptiſm, is as much as if you ſhould carry it to hear a Sermon; and no more ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant than to inſtruct a Stock or Stone, or ſhew ſome godly thing to a blind Man.</note> no charitable Perſon can think the Apoſtle would act contrary to his Commiſſion, to baptize ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Infants, inſtead of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Believers.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 5.</head>
                     <p>Circumciſion was a Seal of the New Covenant to Believers and their Seed under the Law, ſo is Baptiſm to the Seed of Chriſtian Parents under the Goſpel.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>I Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>This Objection is grounded upon <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. where 'tis ſaid, <hi>Abraham received the Sign of Circumciſion,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Some unto whom the Covenant of Grace did not belong, received the Sign of Circumciſion, as <hi>Iſhmael.</hi> God ſaid, the Covenant ſhould not be eſtabliſhed with him, but <hi>Iſaac.</hi> So <hi>Eſau,</hi> and all the Strangers in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi>'s Houſe, or bought with Mony in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that were Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, of whom it may as well be doubted whether the New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-Promiſe did belong to them; therefore they miſtake to ſay Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion was a Seal of the New-Covenant to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi>'s Seed, ſeeing ſome of them had it that were out of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant by the expreſs Word of God. <hi>Gen. 4.19, 20, 21, 25. Gal. 4.29.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>a Seal of the Righteouſneſs of his Faith.</hi> Firſt, Conſider, it's not ſaid, <hi>Circumciſion was a Seal of the New Covenant to</hi> Abraham <hi>and his Seed,</hi> that is begg'd in the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection; the Text ſaith, <hi>It was a Token of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of</hi> Abraham<hi>'s Faith.</hi> But it could not be a Seal of Faith to an Infant which had none. The ſcope of the Apoſtle in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:154397:21"/> this <hi>Chapter</hi> is to ſhew, that <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf was not juſtified by Works, no not by Circumciſion, but by Faith, which he had long before he was Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed. The reaſon of his Circumciſion was, to be a Seal and Confirmation to him, that he by his Faith ſhould be a Father of many Nations; and that the poor <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſhould be accepted of God by Faith, without the Works of the Law, though not circumciſed, ſeeing <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Faith was imputed to him for Righteouſneſs, not when Circumciſed, but Uncircumciſed. This being the ſcope of this Place, a Man had need have a great deal of skill to prove Pedo-Baptiſm from it.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 6.</head>
                     <p>Chriſt ſaid, Suffer little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to come unto me, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>I Anſwer.<note place="margin">Yet Chriſt may be ſaid to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, when his Servants do it by his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note>
                     </head>
                     <p>For what were thoſe Children brought to Chriſt? not to be Baptized, for he Baptized none; 'tis enough for the Lord to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:154397:22"/> his Servants to do it. Theſe Children were brought to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> probably to be touch'd by him to the healing ſome Diſeaſes,<note place="margin">Conſider, here is not one word of Baptiſm in this Scripture. Alſo the Greek word ſignifieth a Child capable of teaching, for 'tis the ſame word, where 'tis ſaid, <hi>Timothy</hi> knew from a Child the Holy Scriptures, that is, ſince he was a Boy, not an Infant. So <hi>Piſcator</hi> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains it.</note> 
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 18. and he <hi>put his Hands upon them, and prayed,</hi> Mat. 19.13. Not to Baptize them; for we cannot imagine our Lord would act contrary to his own Commiſſion, which was, <hi>to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize them who were firſt taught and did believe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Again, becauſe Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Of ſuch is the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Some infer, they may be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, having a right unto the greater, much more to the leſſer. We ſay, this is a <hi>non ſequitur:</hi> It does not follow Perſons may, by Election, have a right to the Kingdom of Glory, yet no right to Goſpel-Ordinances, becauſe under no Obligation to it by any Precept or Promiſe, and wanting thoſe Qualifications which the Goſpel requires. By the ſame Argument Infants may be brought to the Euchariſt, or Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Lord, becauſe, what fits them for the one, fits them for the other.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:154397:22"/>
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 7.</head>
                     <p>If the first Fruit be Holy, the Lump is alſo Holy; if the Root be Holy, ſo are the Branches. Hence ſome would infer a Derivative-Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs from the Parent to the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, therefore to be baptized.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>I Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>This Objection is raiſed from <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.16. The ſcope of the Apoſtle in this place is to ſhew, <hi>That</hi> Abraham, <hi>Father of the Faithful, is the Root; not as a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, but Spiritual Father:</hi> And if we boaſt our ſelves of being Branches of this Root, we muſt have the Faith of our Father <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham;</hi> for the grafting in here does not conſiſt in outward Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, but in ſaving Grace; not in the Viſible, but Inviſible Church by Faith.</p>
                     <p>Mark,<note place="margin">☜</note> none can be called <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Faithful,</hi> but <hi>Abraham</hi> only: No particular Believer, which is but a Branch of this Root, can infer they are a Holy Root to their Poſterity,<note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Cary</hi> of Baptiſm.</note> becauſe <hi>Abraham</hi> is called the <hi>Father of the Faithful,</hi> for <hi>Abraham</hi> is a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:154397:23"/> Spiritual Father, but we are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Natural.</p>
                     <p>In this Chapter, the whole Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Believers are compared un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Olive-tree,</hi> each Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to a Branch, which partakes of the Root and Fatneſs of the Olive-Tree; which Root and Fatneſs is Chriſt, the grafting in is by Faith into the Inviſible Church, which was firſt among the <hi>Jews,</hi> therfore called, <hi>the Olive Tree out of</hi> Abraham <hi>the Root;</hi> who is here ſaid to bear them: for <hi>Abraham</hi> ſtood in a double Capacity,<note place="margin">God was a God unto <hi>Abraham</hi> and his natural Seed, in giving them a literal <hi>Canaan:</hi> unto his Spiritual Seed a God, in giving them a Spiritual <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan.</hi>
                        </note> one as a Natural Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the <hi>Jews,</hi> the other as a Spiritual Father to the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> According to the former Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, ſome are called <hi>Branches</hi> according to Nature; but in the latter, the <hi>Gentiles</hi> are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>wild Olive-Trees</hi> by Nature, yet grafted in by Faith, this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scope.</p>
                     <p>He muſt be a Man of great Learning, that will undertake to prove <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> from this Scripture. Muſt the Child be neceſſarily Holy, and in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:154397:23"/> becauſe the Father is? Muſt the Child be Baptized becauſe the Father is Good? this hath no Warrant from God's Word, which is our Rule.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 8.</head>
                     <p>Many godly learned Men are for Pedo or Infant-Baptiſm.<note place="margin">Many Learned Men are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Infant-Baptiſm, the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts, Nova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Walden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Albigenſes,</hi> Ancient <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains,</hi> Chriſt and his Apoſtles. <hi>Humanum eſt errare.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>I Anſwer</head>
                     <p>With Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi> from <hi>Vadianus,</hi> we paſs over many groſs Errors by the Authority of great Men. Are there not many in the <hi>Roman Communion</hi> who are very Learned? <hi>The Phariſees and Lawyers were Learned Men, who rejected the Counſel of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt themſelves in not being Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized,</hi> Luke 7.30. Say not as they once ſaid, <hi>Have any of the Rulers believed on him?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Godly Men are not to be <hi>imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated in their Errors, but their Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. Elias</hi> was a good Man, yet <hi>called for Fire from Heaven.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Luke 9.</note> We muſt not do ſo. <hi>Luther</hi> was ſound in Juſtification by Faith in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> yet was not to <hi>be</hi> imitated in <hi>Conſubſtantiation,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Aſa</hi> and <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> were good Men, yet
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:154397:24"/> both out in not removing the <hi>High Places,</hi> 1 King. 15.4. That which is called the <hi>Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> had better deſerved that Name, had they ſhut out that Relique of Antichriſt, <hi>Infant-Baptiſm.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 9.</head>
                     <p>Infant-Baptiſm is no where for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>I Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Is it lawful be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den? It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not lawful, becauſe the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth not command it. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Affirmative Command of Chriſt includes a Negative. <hi>Tertullian.</hi>
                        </note>Where-ever Chriſt commands the Baptizing Believers, there is an implicit prohibition of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers not ſo qualified. <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> had no prohibition from uſing ſtrange Fire, yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed for not uſing that Fire upon the Altar which was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and uſing that which the Lord commanded not. By this way of arguing, we may bring in the Baptizing of Bells, as the Book of <hi>Martyrs</hi> tells us of them that did it, and an hundred more Ceremonies of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 10.</head>
                     <p>Thoſe the Apoſtles Baptized, were converted from Paganiſm, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſm, whoſe Parents never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:154397:24"/> in Chriſt, as ours, but were Heathens.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>I Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>There is no more reaſon to baptize the Child of a Believer,<note place="margin">Chriſtianity is not hereditary, as the Son of a Freeman is free; for <hi>Iſaac</hi> had an <hi>Eſau,</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> Sons of <hi>Belial.</hi>
                        </note> than the Child of an Unbeliever as ſuch; and there's the ſame reaſon to baptize the Child of an Infidel, if it believes, as the <hi>Child of a Believer,</hi> upon his or her perſonal Faith: The <hi>worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or unworthineſs of the Parent, does not affect the Children,</hi> ſo as to make them <hi>fitter or unfitter for Goſpel-Ordinances, if they bring forth Fruit meet for Repentance;</hi> tho their Parents were Idolaters, they are proper Subjects of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Ordinances; and if the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents are never ſo Holy, unleſs the Children have perſonal actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Faith, they are not to meddle with God's moſt holy Things.</p>
                     <p>Whereas you ſay, they were <hi>Heathens</hi> the Apoſtles baptized; we ſay, they were <hi>Chriſtians, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers.</hi> Was the Lord Jeſus an <hi>Heathen?</hi> The <hi>Ennuch,</hi> a Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipper of the true God; and <hi>Cornelius</hi>'s Prayers and Alms
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:154397:25"/> came up before God for a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial; but whatever they were before Faith, <hi>Heathens</hi> or <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels,</hi> the Apoſtles baptized them, not until they believed, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> 'Tis moſt likely thoſe who baptize Infants, bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize Heathens; for <hi>we are all the Children of Wrath by Nature,</hi> Eph. 2.3. It is you plead for Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing <hi>Heathens,</hi> we plead for Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing <hi>Believers</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 11.</head>
                     <p>There is no expreſs Command for Womens receiving the Lord's Supper, yet there may be good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences to prove it lawful; ſo of Infant-Baptiſm.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>I Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>Who will ſay there's no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for Women's communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, ſo long as that ſtands upon Record, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. But <hi>let a Man examine himſelf,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> the Common Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</note> 
                        <hi>and ſo let him eat?</hi> The Learned do know the original word ſignifieth <hi>Man or Woman.</hi> The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>There's one Mediator between God and Man;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.5.</note> the word ſignifieth <hi>Man or Woman,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Gal. 3.28.</note> 
                        <hi>Male or Female,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:154397:25"/> all one in Chriſt;</hi> it is the ſame word with the former in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, we read of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men who believed and were Baptized, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.12. ſo are fitly qualified for the Lord's Table. We have alſo an Example of Women's communicating: in <hi>Act.</hi> 1.13, 14. we read, <hi>Mary,</hi> and other Women, with the reſt of the Diſciples, were altogether. And in <hi>Act.</hi> 2.44. it's ſaid, <hi>all that believed were together;</hi> and in <hi>ver.</hi> 42. <hi>theſe continued ſtedfaſtly in the Apoſtles Doctrine, and in Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and in breaking of Bread, and in Prayer.</hi> So that here is a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and an Example for Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens communicating, tho none for Infants Baptiſm, therefore the Objection is falſe and weak.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 12.</head>
                     <p>Infants are Diſciples, therefore they may be Baptized.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>I Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>This Objection being ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on <hi>Act.</hi> 15.10, 11. we ſhall ſhew the Occaſion and Scope of it, and ſee whether it can prove In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:154397:26"/> Diſciples, or that they ought to be Baptized.</p>
                     <p>Some having aſſerted, who came from <hi>Judea, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs a Man was Circumciſed, he could not be ſaved.</hi> Then the Church of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch</hi> determined, that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> with certain of the Church, ſhould go to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to the Apoſtles and Elders, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Queſtion: which when they came together to conſider this Matter, <hi>Peter</hi> roſe up, and ſaid, <hi>Why tempt you God, to put a Yoke upon the Necks of the Diſciples,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Acts 15.10.</hi> This proves not Infants Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, neither that they ought to be baptized.</note> 
                        <hi>which neither our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers nor we were able to bear?</hi> The Meaning of the Apoſtle is, Why ſhould we impoſe the Yoke of Circumciſion upon the Necks of the Diſciples? <hi>viz.</hi> Believing <hi>Gentiles,</hi> which are by no Law obliged unto it; this is to bring us unto that Bondage God hath delivered us from. Now how this doth prove In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants Diſciples, and ſo ought to be Baptized, I leave to all judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Conſiderers.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:154397:26"/>
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 13.</head>
                     <p>Circumciſion nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion avails any thing, but a New Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. We fear Perſons lay too much ſtreſs upon Circumſtantials, not minding the Power of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>I Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>Thoſe who lay too much ſtreſs upon Circumſtantials, 'tis doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs their Evil: But can any lay more ſtreſs upon it, than our Saviour, who though unſpotted, yet would not live without it,<note place="margin">Tho Circumciſion be nothing, which is aboliſhed; is Baptiſm nothing, which is called Righteouſneſs, and the Counſel of God?</note> and calls it <hi>Righteouſneſs?</hi> The laying the ſtreſs of our Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs upon Chriſt, ſhould not hinder but further Obedience; and always doth, where the Faith is of the right Kind.</p>
                     <p>And whereas the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Circumciſion avails not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing;</hi> it did avail ſomething, when God threatned <hi>Moſes</hi> with Death for not circumciſing his Son, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4. And when God ſaid, <hi>Whoever was not Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſhould be cut off from among the People,</hi> Gen. 17.14.</p>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:154397:27"/>
                     <p>The Apoſtle never intended to undermine Goſpel-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, by ſaying, <hi>Circumciſion nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion avails any thing;</hi> for in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.19. he adds, <hi>but the keeping the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God.</hi> What tho Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion is nothing, becauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed; is Believers Baptiſm nothing, which is a ſtanding Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance?</p>
                     <p>What tho ſome <hi>Jews</hi> might lay more ſtreſs upon Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than upon the Lord Jeſus for Salvation? which might be the principal Cauſe of the Apoſtle's thus ſpeaking: I hope Perſons have more charity than to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, we lay more ſtreſs upon Baptiſm than our Lord's Merits.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 14.</head>
                     <p>If Children may not be Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed under the Goſpel, their Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg is leſs than under the Law.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>I Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>The Priviledg under the Law, and under the Goſpel, is the ſame to Infants as to the Covenant of Grace; and as for Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it was indeed a Priviledg to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:154397:27"/> the <hi>Jews</hi> in compariſon of the <hi>Heathens,</hi> but called <hi>a Yoke</hi> in compariſon of them under the Goſpel.</p>
                     <p>We grant,<note place="margin">Why ſhould this be eſteemed the loſs of a Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, more than not enjoying li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terally a holy Land, a holy City, Temple, or Succeſſion of a High Prieſt and Prieſthood by Generation?</note> it's a great Mercy for Children to have Godly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, having the advantage of a good Education, Prayer, and good Examples. But what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit can Infants have from Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, when God never appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it for them, nor made any Promiſe to them in it? but moſt <hi>glorious ones</hi> are made to ſuch as believe and are baptized, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Remiſſion of Sins, the Gift of the Holy Ghoſt, and Eternal Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> Mark 16.16.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 15.</head>
                     <p>The Children of Believers are Holy, therefore they ought to be Baptized.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>I Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>By explaining the Scripture upon which the Objection is grounded, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle is here giving an anſwer to a Caſe of Conſcience; that is, Whether it were lawful for the believing Husband or Wife,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:154397:28"/> to leave or depart from the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing Wife or Husband? The Apoſtle in the Negative an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, By no means; for theſe Reaſons. Firſt, Now your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are Holy, <hi>viz.</hi> lawfully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten in Wedlock; but if the Husband leaves the Wife,<note place="margin">The Greek Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, is well tranſlated <hi>to</hi> by the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva.</hi>
                        </note> or Wife the Husband, every one will count your Children un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, that is, <hi>Baſtards,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore don't part, but live toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe the unbelieving Husband is ſanctified or ſet apart by God's Ordinance to the uſe of the Wife, and the Wife to the uſe of the Husband, in a matrimonial way, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14.</p>
                     <p>This is not an inherent ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, nor a federal Holineſs, as ſome would beg, and therefore argue for Baptiſm; this Holineſs is a legitimate Holineſs: And there can be no more concluded, becauſe theſe Children are ſaid to be Holy, therefore to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, than the Baptizing <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rias</hi>'s Bells or Pots in the Lord's Houſe, becauſe they are ſaid to be Holy, <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.20.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:154397:28"/>
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 16.</head>
                     <p>All Nations are to be Baptized; Infants are a part of the Nation, <hi>Ergo,</hi> Infants may be baptized.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>I Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>The Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Go ye therefore and teach all Nations,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, Diſciple all Nations; but that muſt be firſt by Preaching and Inſtructing them in the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Chriſtian Faith. <hi>And addeth,</hi> I cannot be of their mind who think, that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized before taught. <hi>Pool's</hi> Synopſis on <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.</note> 
                        <hi>Baptizing them,</hi> &amp;c. Never intending any ſhould be baptized but what were firſt taught. 'Tis as if a King ſhould give a Commiſſion to an Herauld, to proclaim throughout his Dominions, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever in the Nation, Male or Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, would go to School and learn the Greek Tongue, ſhould have a Wedg of Gold; Doth this follow that every one in the Nation ſhould have a Wedg of Gold, becauſe a part of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? No, not unleſs they do learn the Greek Tongue. So in like manner,<note place="margin">A dreadful piece of Infant-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm appeared, when the Heads of <hi>6000</hi> Infants were found mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and buried in a Warren near a Monaſtry.</note> no more in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are to be baptized, than what are firſt taught and learn Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>Chriſt did no more intend that every one in the Nation ſhould be baptized, than the Prophet
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:154397:29"/> 
                        <hi>Haggai</hi> did,<note place="margin">So ſuperſtitiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly zealous were ſome in the 7th Century for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm, that a dead Child was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the Grave and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened, its Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Name gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto it.</note> that every indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual in the Nations of the World would deſire our Lord's coming, becauſe, he ſaith, <hi>the Deſire of all Nations ſhould come, Hag.</hi> 2.7. which is only the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers in all Nations.</p>
                     <p>God did not intend Infants had robbed him, when he ſaid, <hi>Ye have robbed me, even this whole Nation,</hi> they being not capable of it: No more are Infants of Baptiſm, tho a part of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, being not firſt taught and made Diſciples, according to the Commiſſion.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 17.</head>
                     <p>Men of Years were firſt Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, afterwards Infants: So in the Goſpel, Baptiſm was firſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred unto Men and Women, but afterwards Infants were Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>I Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>You ſay well, <hi>Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were baptized first;</hi> Infants were never baptized, by virtue of <hi>a Commiſſion from Chriſt,</hi> tho Believers were; and it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout three hundred Years after
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:154397:29"/> Chriſt before any Infant was Sprinkled.<note place="margin">Danvers <hi>on Baptiſm,</hi> p. 204.</note> Chriſt's Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was to baptize Believers: now unleſs any can ſhow where this was abrogated, and a new Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for Baptizing Infants gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, this remains, and will to the end of the World.</p>
                     <p>Indeed <hi>Abraham</hi> was Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed when he was old, as a Seal of the Righteouſneſs of his Faith, to aſſure him <hi>he ſhould be a Father of many Nations,</hi> a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Father unto <hi>Believers, Jews,</hi> and <hi>Gentiles:</hi> And after this God, commanded him to Circumciſe his natural Seed; and when any can ſhew us as plain a Command for Believers to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize their Infant-Seed, as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> had to Circumciſe his, the Controverſy ſhall end.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 18.</head>
                     <p>Infant-Baptiſm is an Apoſtolical Tradition;<note place="margin">Tho this Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in any Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Book, yet it is of no leſs Authority with us than the Scripture. <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine.</hi>
                        </note> and though the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be ſilent in the Caſe, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interrupted Tradition and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage of the Church makes up that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:154397:30"/>
                     <head>I Anſwer,</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <p>Tradition ought to be proved by more than one E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, <hi>viz. Origen,</hi> whom all other Ages have condemned of Errors.</p>
                           <p>Dr. <hi>Taylor.</hi> And whoſe Works are ſo ſpurious, that he that reads them, knows not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he reads <hi>Origen</hi> or <hi>Ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finus. Eraſm.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </note>With Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> 
                        <q>Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> muſt by all means ſupply the place of Scripture; and there is pretended a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition Apoſtolical, that Infants were Baptized: But at this, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> we are not much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, for we who rely upon the written Word of God as ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to eſtabliſh all true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, do not value the Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Tradition.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>The pretended Proof for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm, being an Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Tradition, from <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the <hi>Areopagite, Juſtin Martyr</hi>'s <hi>Reſponſes, Origen</hi>'s <hi>Homilies, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> in an Epiſtle to one <hi>Fidas</hi> a Prieſt, have been examined, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed, and found fabulous and forged. <hi>Danvers</hi> on Baptiſm, <hi>pag.</hi> 133, to 150.</p>
                     <p>It is very improbable that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm ſhould be an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Tradition, when decreed by ſeveral Councils in the 4th Century, the Council of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage,</hi> of <hi>Neoceſarea</hi> and <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicea,</hi> &amp;c. they did hold forth
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:154397:30"/> the neceſſity of Confeſſion and Profeſſion, before Baptiſm.</p>
                     <p>In ſhort, It is againſt the Reaſon of a Man to conclude this an Apoſtolical Tradition, becauſe this were to make the Apoſtles act beyond their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, which were to Baptize only Believers.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 19.</head>
                     <p>Infants were once Church-Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and that Law was never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brogated, neither do we find they were cut off.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>I Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptist</hi> abrogated this ſufficiently, when he told the <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Sadduces,</hi> it was a vain Plea to ſay, <hi>Abraham was their Father;</hi> that was a good Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument for Infant-Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip under the Law by Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, but ſignified nothing to Church-memberſhip under the Goſpel by Baptiſm, now the Diſpenſation is alter'd: <hi>If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bring not forth good Fruit in his own Perſon, the Ax being laid to the Root of the Tree, it is to be hewn down and caſt into Eternal
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:154397:31"/> Fire.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.20. ends this Controverſy plain enough, where he aſſerts, the natural Branches were bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off by Unbelief; and if they come to believe, they may be grafted in again;<note place="margin">Who can ſhew any Inſtance where Infants were accounted Members of the Church under the Goſpel?</note> but until then, they remain broken off, and that Law of Infant-Church-memberſhip is as plainly abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated under the Goſpel, as the Paſſover and Circumciſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which all grant is void, tho not ſo formally done as once com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, there being no need; the Subſtance being come, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily Shadows ceaſe.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 20.</head>
                     <p>In <hi>Mat. 3.11.</hi> John Baptiſt ſaid, <hi>I Baptize you with Water unto Repentance:</hi> And in the 6th Verſe, —<hi>Were Baptized of</hi> John <hi>in</hi> Jordan, <hi>confeſſing their Sins.</hi> Here, ſay ſome, is Baptiſm before Confeſſion or Repentance, in the order of words: therefore we being Baptized in our Infancy, if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and confeſs our Sins after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, 'tis ſufficient, and we need not be Baptized again.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:154397:31"/>
                     <head>I Anſwer.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. If you were only ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Infancy, you were never yet Baptized.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. 'Tis ſaid, <hi>they were Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in</hi> Jordan, <hi>confeſſing their Sins;</hi> but I never heard of an Infant confeſs Sin in the Act of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> as theſe did. I will glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Baptize any Souls that ſhall truly confeſs themſelves Sinners in the very Act and Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Ordinance, to the Glory of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> who came to ſave Sinners.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Tho the Text ſays, <hi>I Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize you unto Repentance,</hi> none dare ſay that <hi>John</hi> Baptized them before they did manifeſt Repentance; becauſe when ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Saddu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> came unto <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm, he ſaid, <hi>O Generation of Vipers,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm is called, The Baptiſm of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Sins, becauſe Chriſt preached Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Sins to the Penitent Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever. <hi>Piſcator</hi> on <hi>Mark 1.4.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>bring forth Fruit meet for Repentance, and think not to ſay, you have</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham <hi>to your Father.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4. <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm is called, <hi>the Baptiſm of Repentance,</hi> Mark 1.4. Can any other be the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing than this, that <hi>John</hi> was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:154397:32"/> of God to demand <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance from dead Works,</hi> of all that were Baptized, and Faith alſo in him that was to come? <hi>Acts</hi> 19. and upon this <hi>John</hi> did preach unto them <hi>the Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Sin.</hi> I think it never did enter into any Man's Heart, that <hi>John</hi> did firſt Baptize, before he examined them of Repentance and Faith in the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> to come.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. To Baptize unto Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, the ſenſe can be nothing elſe than my Baptiſm, being the Baptiſm of Repentance: <hi>I Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize them, for my Baptiſm is the Baptiſm of Repentance;</hi> I muſt ſee ſomething of that, elſe I have no Commiſſion to Baptize.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Penitent Souls may well be ſaid to be Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed unto Repentance,<note place="margin">Should I ſay, Sir <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Rawleigh</hi> was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed in <hi>Palace-Yard,</hi> and made an excellent Speech, none would underſtand that he ſpoke after he was dead, becauſe Beheaded is firſt, and Speech af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So tho <hi>John,</hi> ſay I, baptized to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, it could not be he baptized firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he required Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and Faith, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Chriſt's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, as neceſſary to Baptiſm.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'tis an every day's Work, after his Baptiſm, to amend and reform. However <hi>John</hi>'s words may be placed, the ſcope of the Place ſheweth, they muſt repent before they were baptized, becauſe,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:154397:32"/> when the <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Sadduces</hi> came to his Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, that is, to be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, ſaid he, <hi>O Generation of Vipers, bring forth first Fruits meet for Repentance;</hi> or unto or according to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of true Repentance, <hi>and then I will baptize you, and not without it.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 21.</head>
                     <p>Water-Baptiſm is <hi>John</hi>'s Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. <hi>Paul</hi> was not ſent to Baptize: We have the Subſtance, we need not the Shadow; we are baptized with the Spirit, we need not that of Water.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>I Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>Cornelius <hi>and his Houſhold were baptized with the Holy Ghoſt, to that degree, as they ſpake with Tongues,</hi> Acts 10. <hi>yet thought it not beneath them to ſubmit to Christ's bleſſed Ordinance of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Baptiſm.</hi> I know not but this Scripture may be an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Teſtimony againſt ſome which pretend to the Spirit, who have it in that degree, as now <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his Houſhold;
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:154397:33"/> 
                        <hi>Where the Spirit is,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Acts 10.44, <hi>to</hi> 48.</note> 
                        <hi>there is Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Command.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I marvel any who pretend to great degrees of the Spirit, ſhould call God's Ordinances Shadows and Shells: Is it a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt, and a Shadow? did Chriſt ever call it ſo? Thou may'ſt as well ſay, all other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances are Shadows, as Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Preaching, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And where wilt thou run? is it a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand? hath it a Divine Stamp? if ſo, diſpute not Chriſt's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. Are you wiſer than he who ſubjected himſelf to it? or can you think you have more of the Spirit, than him who had it without meaſure, and yet was was baptized in Water?</p>
                     <p>Whereas it is Objected, Chriſt ſent not<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Bullinger</hi> in his Houſe-book ſaith, of <hi>1 Cor. 1.17.</hi> 'Tis not ſlightly to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, as if <hi>Paul</hi> was not ſent to baptize at all, but that Teaching ſhould go before Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, for the Lord commanded both Teaching, and Adminiſtring Sacraments.</note> 
                        <hi>Paul</hi> to Baptize, but to Preach, <hi>Paul</hi> did baptize ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral: either he did it by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, or Preſumption; ſurely not by the latter, therefore the former. His meaning is, that Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm was not his firſt and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Work; he was ſent to preach, and Baptiſm fell in as a part of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:154397:33"/> his Preaching-Office.<note place="margin">
                           <p>None are fit for Goſpel-Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, until they have the Spirit of God.</p>
                           <p>Doth <hi>Corneli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> and his Houſe ſubmit to Water-Baptiſm, after Baptized emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently with the Spirit? then that can be no Argument, we are Baptized with the Spirit, and need no Water.</p>
                        </note> This is cleared by our Lord's Word, who ſaid, <hi>I am not ſent but to the loſt Sheep of the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>not but he came alſo to be a Light to the Gentiles;</hi> he was firſt to preach to them, hence called, <hi>the Miniſter of the Circumciſion.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And whereas Water-Baptiſm is called <hi>John</hi>'s <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> I query the Baptiſm of <hi>John,</hi> Was it from Heaven, or of Men? If from Heaven, as it was, (for God ſent him to Baptize) then let all keep ſilent. I know no difference between <hi>John</hi>'s Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and that Chriſt gave his Apoſtles, but that the former Baptized <hi>in the Name of Christ to come,</hi> the latter <hi>in his Name being come.</hi> Whereas ſome urge, <hi>John</hi> ſaid, <hi>He muſt decreaſe, Chriſt increaſe.</hi> This hath no reference to the ceaſing of Goſpel-Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, but unto the Splendor and Glory of Chriſt in the World, above what <hi>John</hi>'s was in Holineſs and Miracles; for <hi>John</hi> did no Miracle, <hi>John</hi> 10.41.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:154397:34"/>
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 22.</head>
                     <p>There are no fit Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; therefore, for the preſent, Sacraments and Church-Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ceaſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>I Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>When Chriſt gave Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>Preach,</hi> he gave Power in the ſame to <hi>Baptize,</hi> Mat. 28. How comes this to paſs, that thoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Perſons which thus object, <hi>do Preach,</hi> which requires as great Ability and Sanctity to the due performance of the one as of the other.</p>
                     <p>I know ſome object that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion (<hi>Mat.</hi> 28.) laſted no longer than to the end of that Age.</p>
                     <p>To which I Anſwer, Then Preaching ended too: Chriſt commands his Diſciples <hi>to teach all Nations</hi> all things which he commanded them; Now Chriſt's Commands were, <hi>Holineſs, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> and <hi>Faith;</hi> was this to be no longer than to the end of that Age? was Chriſt's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of his Preſence but to the end of that Age? this would be
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:154397:34"/> uncomfortable Doctrine. The Promiſe is, <hi>I will be with you to the end of the World;</hi> the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned know it's the ſame original Word as in <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.39, 40. where it is ſaid, <hi>The Harveſt is the end of the World: As the Tares are gathered together, and burnt in the Fire, ſo ſhall it be in the end of the World.</hi> All conclude, (I think) or ought, that this hath reſpect to the final end of all things;<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> this being the ſame word in <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. We conclude, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpel, baptizing them which are taught, and the graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Preſence of Chriſt,<note place="margin">If Baptiſm end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Age, then preaching of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, Faith, and Holineſs ceaſed alſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all in the ſame Commiſſion. Yea, the promiſe of Chriſt's Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence must ceaſe alſo in the end of that Age: a more uncomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Doctrine cannot be.</note> is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in his Church till the World's end, that is, till the <hi>final end of all things.</hi> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, <hi>Paul</hi> aſſerts, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.21. that <hi>Christ will have a Church, and glory in the Churches through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Ages, World without end.</hi> From whence I argue, if God have a Church in all Ages, he muſt have Ordinances there, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no Church of Chriſt can be conſtituted without them: If there be Ordinances in the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:154397:35"/> Church in all Ages, there muſt be ſome to adminiſter them, or elſe they would be inſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant.</p>
                     <p>But that he hath fit Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrators in the Church, and will have, <hi>Paul</hi> aſſerts, in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.12, 13. <hi>He gave ſome Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, ſome Evangeliſts, ſome Paſtors and Teachers,</hi> (For what end?) <hi>for the perfecting of the Saints, for the Work of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, for the edifying the Body of Chriſt,</hi> (How long?) <hi>till we all come to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Faith, and of the Knowledg of the Son of God, unto a perfect Man, unto the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Fulneſs of Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Let Men take heed how they put a ſlight upon the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God in crying up the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, with a ſecret Deſign to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry the Holy Scriptures; crying up the Power of Godlineſs in Word, to undermine the Form of Godlineſs; cry up Faith, and Juſtification by Faith, to leſſen Repentance and a holy Life; cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out againſt the Error of all Churches, and under that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:154397:35"/> leave the true Church, and the Communion of Saints, until at laſt they have loſt the Church in the Wilderneſs, the ready way to loſe themſelves too, if Grace prevent not, which I deſire may.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Contains the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
               <p n="1">1. IF it be their Duty, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, to be Baptized: then I infer, thoſe who are not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of this Grace of Faith, are under no Divine Obligation, nor their Parents neither, to Baptize them, 'tis only a piece of Will-worſhip, which God never required, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.23.</p>
               <p>If any reckon themſelves ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to Baptize, or be Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, from Mens Authority, let ſuch baptize in their Name of whom they have this Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and not join the Name of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:154397:36"/> Chriſt with humane Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Baptiſm of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, was not practiſed for near <hi>300</hi> Years after Christ; nor enjoined, as neceſſary, till <hi>400</hi> Years after Christ. <hi>Magde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> Hiſt. Cent. <hi>5.</hi> p. <hi>835. Danvers</hi> on Baptim, <hi>p. 105, 106, 107, 108, 109.</hi>
                  </note>Infant-Baptiſm was hardly heard of till about three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years after Chriſt. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> was the firſt that preached it neceſſary, in his heat againſt <hi>Pelagius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> who denied Original Sin, which <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſuppoſed to be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in Baptiſm about the 5th Century; it was confirmed and decreed by the Pope and his Council, in the <hi>Milevetan Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil,</hi> a Province in <hi>Africa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Is Faith to precede Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm? Then how irregular do they act, who baptize firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Subject hath any Grace, and know not whether ever they will? Our Lord knew how he placed his words, when he ſaid, <hi>Believe, and be baptized;</hi> and for Perſons to act contrary, reflects upon the Wiſdom of Chriſt, as though they knew it were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Baptize firſt, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Lord ſaid to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:154397:36"/>3. Is Faith to precede Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm? Then we infer, thoſe who are in this practice, are very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly called <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Perſons Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in Infancy, are to be Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed after they believe, which is not to be eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Rebaptiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but right Baptiſm, as <hi>Peter Bruce</hi> the great Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſian Martyr.</note> 
                  <hi>Rebap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizers.</hi> We know but of one Baptiſm, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. and that is Believers, having the Broad-Seal, and Stamp of Divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority upon it: how in deriſion are ſuch called <hi>Catabaptiſts,</hi> as if they were againſt Baptiſm, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they plead for <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution</hi> againſt Mens Inventions?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Is Faith to precede Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm? Then we infer, they are greatly Heterodox who aſſert, that Baptiſm works Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the very<note n="*" place="margin">Some call it <hi>Opus opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi>
                  </note> Act; altho we doubt not of the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the Holy Spirit to ſtrengthen and comfort God's People in the Way of their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: But to ſay the very Act works it, is not allowable, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as Regeneration is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired before it; and this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is a Sign and Significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Regeneration, therefore called by the Apoſtle, <hi>the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Regeneration,</hi> Tit. 3.5.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:154397:37"/> 
                  <hi>Death to Sin, and Sanctification, is figured out in this Ordinance, when Perſons are buried with Chriſt in Baptiſm,</hi> Rom. 6.4.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Grotius</hi> ſaith, in his Annotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon <hi>Matth. 19.</hi> The Synod of <hi>Neoceſarea</hi> decreed, a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with Child might be Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, becauſe it reached not the Fruit of the Womb, foraſmuch as in Baptiſm each one's free choice is ſhewed.</note>5. Are Perſons to believe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Baptiſm? Then an actual perſonal Faith is to precede this Ordinance; 'tis not the Faith of the Church, nor an imputative Faith of the Parents in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, nor the Faith of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſips or Sureties, can be a ſufficient Argument for any Miniſter to Baptize, but a profeſſion of their own Faith, as <hi>Philip</hi> required of the <hi>Eunuch, Act.</hi> 8.37. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſome aſſert, Infants have Faith; what they may have, is not known by any Sign appears in them:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>See Dr.</hi> Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veil, <hi>on</hi> Acts 8.</note> And for perſonal and actual <hi>Faith</hi> they have none, which the Commiſſion requires as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>requiſite to Baptiſm. And for any to aſſert Infants have Faith, or any other inſpired Habit, may we not ſay with Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> ſuch are conſtrained to anſwer this without Revelation againſt Reaſon, common Senſe, and all the Experience in the World?
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:154397:37"/> no greater Advantage can be deſired againſt ſuch a Poſition.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Is Faith to be profeſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are Baptized? Then we infer, thoſe that have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in defence of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, had a good Foundation for what they did.</p>
               <p>The Waldenſian Chriſtians ſuffered Impriſonment,<note place="margin">Danvers <hi>on Baptiſm,</hi> p. 113, 114.</note> confiſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Goods, and ſome Death. Many in <hi>Germany, Holland, Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Vienna, Mentz,</hi> the <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate,</hi> for their oppoſing <hi>Pedo-Baptiſm,</hi> and aſſerting <hi>Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. Let all Believers be exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to obey Chriſt, who yet lie ſhort of their Duty; the King or Subject, Paſtor or Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Learned or Illiterate: for the King of Kings hath done it, the great Shepheard of the Sheep, and he who is only wiſe.</p>
               <p>If any Object, <hi>I was Baptized in my Infancy.</hi> I Anſwer,</p>
               <p>As one ſaith of Marriage, It's not the Bed that maketh Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:154397:38"/> for then Fornication is Marriage, but it's a lawful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent by Covenant. So I ſay of Baptiſm, It's not a little Water ſprinkled upon the Face makes Baptiſm, but alſo Conſent and Subjection to Chriſt's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
               <p>When thou waſt an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſaith, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring Covenant with God, is the eſſential point of Baptiſm; without it, it is not Baptiſm. Children cannot Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; Sureties neither by the Law of God, nor Nature ought not; Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents by the Canon Law muſt not.</note> thou gaveſt no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but rather Diſſent, by crying when the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was ſcatter'd upon thy Face; thou hadſt no Faith, no Love, no active Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; thy Judgment not informed, thy Will and Affections not inclined, but wholly paſſive in the thing,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Barlow</hi> ſaith, In the Primitive Times, Perſons were firſt <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecumini,</hi> then <hi>Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minati</hi> or <hi>Baptizati.</hi> If Matter and Form be wanting the Eſſence of the O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>inance is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> like a Stock or Stone, ſo that thou art not yet Baptized, becauſe there wanted then the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Eſſence of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which is right Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Form: as for Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, an ignorant Infant was the Subject, in the room of an underſtanding Believer: For the Form, Sprinkling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:154397:38"/> of Dipping, ſo that thy Infant-Baptiſm is a meer <hi>non entity,</hi> and nothing.</p>
               <p>The Church of the <hi>Rome</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, ſhe changed Dipping in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Sprinkling. <hi>Cyprian</hi> is the firſt who pleads for Baptizing the Sick by Sprinkling, and for Sprinkling new Converts in the Priſon-Houſe:<note place="margin">Danvers, <hi>p.</hi> 204, 205, 206. Magd. <hi>Cent.</hi> 3. <hi>C.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 126.</note> By degrees they brought it in for Sick Children, then for all Children.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rome</hi>'s firſt and great Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Novatians</hi> and <hi>Donatiſts</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Infant-Baptiſm.</note> by which Infant-Baptiſm was brought in, was their ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining it took away Original-Sin: Upon which they made this Canon in the <hi>Milevetan</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>It is our Will,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Too many are very tenacious of this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment now.</note> 
                  <hi>That all who affirm young Children have Everlaſting Life, which are not Baptized, to the taking away of Original Sin, ſhall be Anathemized.</hi>
               </q>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:154397:39"/>
               <q>
                  <bibl>So in the Fifth Council at <hi>Carthage.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Fifth Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> in the Year <hi>416.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>We will, That whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver denieth that little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by Baptiſm are not freed from Perdition, and eternally ſaved, that they be accurſed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>This was firſt confirmed by Pope <hi>Innocentius</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> with Seventy Biſhops: Had the Pope and Council decreed, that the Imputation of Chriſt's Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs unto Children, took away Original Sin, in the room of their Infant-Baptiſm, it had been much ſounder Doctrine.</p>
               <div type="motives">
                  <head>MOTIVES.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt;</hi> Sincere Obedience to the Precepts, gives you a right to the Promiſes annexed, which is, <hi>Remiſſion of Sin, the Gift of the Holy Ghoſt, and Divine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:154397:39"/>2dly,<note place="margin">This is <hi>Janus Sacramento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> ſay the Ancients.</note> By this Gate you enter into the Enjoyment of all Church-Priviledges, which are very great and many. Hence Holy <hi>David</hi> preferr'd <hi>one Day in God's Courts, more than a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand in an ungodly King's Palace.</hi> The Communion of Saints is a bleſſed Thing; but you cannot have this orderly,<note place="margin">Faith the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation-Principle of Salvation; but Baptiſm the Foundation-Principle of Church-Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution.</note> without firſt being Baptized; the three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand converted <hi>Jews</hi> were Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized before added to the Church: And in breaking Bread, Chriſt himſelf was Baptized be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he preached and broke Bread with his Diſciples.</p>
                  <p n="3">3dly, Sincere Acts of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, increaſe Peace in the Soul like a River; yea,<note place="margin">One Act of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Obedience is more to God than if we could give him many Worlds. <hi>Pſal. 50.8, 14.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>the Peace of God, which paſſeth all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> We have heard of ſome which have died uncomfortably, for not obeying Chriſt in this Ordinance according to their Light.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Finally;</hi> By this Act you will obey a moſt glorious Precept, follow a moſt glorious Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, have a right to moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:154397:40"/> Promiſes, enter into a moſt glorious Communion; and to conclude, you will put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice an Ordinance, which will be a Pledg unto you, of Sins Remiſſion, your free Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and your Soul's Salvation: a Reward more than enough for our poor Obedience.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Contains plain Scriptures for Believers-Baptiſm, which ſatisfieth the Conſcience bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than far-fetch'd Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MAtth. 3.13.</hi> Then cometh Jeſus to <hi>John</hi> to be Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed. <hi>Verſ. 15.</hi> And Jeſus ſaid, Suffer it to be ſo now; for thus it becometh us to fulfil all Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>Verſ. 16.</hi> And Jeſus, when he was Baptized, went up ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way out of the Water.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:154397:40"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acts 2.38.</hi> Repent, and be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized every one of you, in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acts 8.12.</hi> They were Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, both Men and Women.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acts 8.36.</hi> And the Eunuch ſaid, See, here is Water, what doth hinder me to be Baptized? <hi>Verſ. 37.</hi> And <hi>Philip</hi> ſaid, If thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveſt with all thine Heart, thou mayeſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acts 10.47.</hi> Can any forbid Water, that theſe ſhould not be Baptized, which have received the Holy Ghoſt as well as we. <hi>Verſ. 48.</hi> And he commanded them to be Baptized in the Name of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acts 22.16.</hi> And now why tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieſt thou? Ariſe, and be Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and waſh away thy Sins.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acts 9.18.</hi> And he aroſe, and was Baptized.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mat. 28.19.</hi> Go, teach all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Baptizing them in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acts 2.41.</hi> Then they that glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly received his Word, were Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:154397:41"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mark 16.16.</hi> He that believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and is Baptized, ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mat. 21.25.</hi> The Baptiſm of <hi>John,</hi> whence was it? from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or of Men? If we ſay, From Heaven; he will ſay unto us, Why did ye not believe him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luke 20.6.</hi> But if we ſay of Men, all the People will ſtone us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acts 18.8.</hi> And <hi>Criſpus</hi> the chief Ruler of the Synagogue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved on the Lord with all his Houſe: and many of the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> hearing, believed, and were Baptized.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rom. 6.4.</hi> We are buried with him by Baptiſm.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luke 7.29.</hi> The Publicans ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified God, being Baptized. <hi>Verſ. 30.</hi> But the Phariſees, and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, rejected the Counſel of God againſt themſelves, not being Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John 4.1.</hi> Jeſus made and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized more Diſciples than <hi>John.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gal. 3.27.</hi> As many as have been Baptized into Chriſt, have put on Chriſt.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:154397:41"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eph. 4.5.</hi> One Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>1 Pet. 3.21.</hi> The like Figure whereunto Baptiſm doth ſave us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acts 16.33.</hi> And he took them the ſame Hour of the Night, and waſhed their Stripes; and was Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, he and all his, ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; <hi>Verſ. 34.</hi> He believing in God with all his Houſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John 3.23. John</hi> was Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing in <hi>Enon,</hi> near <hi>Salim,</hi> becauſe there was much Water there.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Heb. 6.1, 2.</hi> Of the Doctrine of Baptiſms, <hi>(called God's Oracle)</hi> a Principle of the Doctrine of Chriſt, and a Foundation-Principle. <hi>Heb. 5.14.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John 3.22.</hi> After theſe things came Jeſus and his Diſciples into the Land of <hi>Judea,</hi> and there he tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried and Baptized.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luke 3.21.</hi> Jeſus being Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, the Heavens were opened. <hi>Verſ. 23.</hi> Jeſus himſelf being about thirty Years of Age.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 12.13.</hi> By one Spirit are we all Baptized into one Body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:154397:42"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Contains an Account of the People of God, called <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts;</hi> their great Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, for maintaining Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers-Baptiſm in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto Infant-Baptiſm.</head>
               <p>IN the 4th <hi>Lateran</hi> Council, Canons were made to baniſh the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> for <hi>Hereticks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and <hi>Honorius</hi> made and publiſhed the following E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, in the Year 413. <hi>viz. That the Perſon rebaptized, as well as the Adminiſtrator, ſhould be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with Death.</hi> One <hi>Alba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> a zealous Miniſter, was put to death, with others, upon the ſaid Edict.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Zurick</hi> it was decreed, <hi>If any preſumed to Baptize any that were Baptized in Infancy, they ſhould be drowned.</hi> And that at <hi>Vienna,</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:154397:42"/> many for Baptizing ſuch, were ſo tied together in Chains, that they drew the other after him in the River.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Ropleſteim,</hi> the Lords of that Place decreed, <hi>That ſuch ſhould be burned with an hot Iron, and bear the baſe Brand of thoſe Lords in whoſe Lands they had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that through <hi>Germany, Alſatia,</hi> and <hi>Sweeden,</hi> many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of this Sect, <hi>who</hi> (as they word it) <hi>defiled their first Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm with a Second,</hi> were the third time Baptized in their own Blood. Dr. <hi>Featly</hi> out of <hi>Gaſſius,</hi> pag. 68, 182.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Heribertus, Liſonius,</hi> and <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanus,</hi> with eleven more <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> were burnt at <hi>Orleans</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> for oppoſing Childrens Baptiſm.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Goſlar,</hi> in the Time of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the Third, ſeveral were put to Death for oppoſing Infant-Baptiſm.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gerardus</hi> burnt, for oppoſing the Romiſh Church in this Point.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:154397:43"/>
               <p>By the Decree of <hi>Alfonſus,</hi> five Men and three Women were burnt at <hi>Troys</hi> in <hi>Campagn, Anno</hi> 1200.</p>
               <p>Nineteen Perſons condemned and burnt in the Biſhoprick of <hi>Tholouſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Four Monks which were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted from the Romiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, were by Pope <hi>John</hi> the 22d burnt, for oppoſing Infant-Baptiſm.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Cremor</hi> in <hi>Auſtria,</hi> many of the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> were burnt, for oppoſing Pedobaptiſm.</p>
               <p>A pious Woman in <hi>Flanders,</hi> named <hi>Peronne,</hi> was burnt in the profeſſion of this Faith, with many more.</p>
               <p>The firſt Edict of <hi>Zurick,</hi> 1525. five Years after <hi>Zwingli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> began the Reformation, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their own departure from <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In <hi>Edw. 4.</hi> and <hi>Hen. 8.</hi> many of thoſe burnt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Name of <hi>Lollards.</hi> Hence we read in Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> of <hi>Lollards Tower.</hi>
                  </note> commands all ſorts to Baptize their Children, and to forbear Rebaptization, upon the penalty of Pecuniary Mulcts and Impriſonments. The ſecond E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict extended to Baniſhment, Confiſcation, and Death; this
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:154397:43"/> was five Years after, in 1530.</p>
               <p>Many ſtarved and died in Priſon.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Newburgh,</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no 1653. baniſhed all the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> out of his Country, who thereupon diſperſe themſelves into the Dukedom of <hi>Cleave</hi> and <hi>Brandenburgh.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="abstract">
                  <head>An Abſtract of the bloody Edict of the Emperor, <hi>Charles</hi> the 5th of <hi>Spain,</hi> made <hi>June</hi> 1535. againſt the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> or <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſian Chriſtians,</hi> and the execution thereof in the <hi>Seventeen Provinces,</hi> viz.</head>
                  <p>COmmanding all Perſons to renounce thoſe Perſwaſions and Practices, and refrain the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing the ſame, by Preaching, or otherwiſe, upon penalty of forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Life and Goods, without Mercy: The Men to be burnt, the Women to be drowned. And all
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:154397:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> that Conceal, Harbour, and do not in their Places proſecute the Law againſt them, to ſuffer the ſame Penalty. And that thoſe that diſcover them, to have the third part of their Eſtates; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding all Mediation or Interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, upon ſevere Puniſhment.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Many hundreds ſuffered Death upon this Edict, and what his Son</hi> Philip <hi>made in 1556.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thus you ſee Chriſt's Words made good,</hi> His People ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for Righteouſneſs ſake.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>See this Chapte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> much enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, in</hi> Danvers <hi>on B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ptiſm.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:154397:44"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Contains an Epitome of this Book, in a Compariſon of Believers-Baptiſm and Infant-Baptiſm together.</head>
               <div type="epitome">
                  <head>Believers-Baptiſm.</head>
                  <p>GOd hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Text, <hi>That all who believe, and are Baptized, ſhall be ſaved,</hi> Mark 16.16.</p>
                  <p>There is a lively Similitude between Chriſt's Death, Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial, Reſurrection, and Believers being buried in Baptiſm, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4.</p>
                  <p>Believers Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, are converted, and ſhall never come into Condemnation, <hi>John</hi> 5.24.</p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:154397:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>Believers Baptized, love God, and keep his Commandments, <hi>John</hi> 14.15.</p>
                  <p>It's Chriſt's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, that Teaching, Repenting, and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede and go before Baptiſm, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18, 19.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe who bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize Believers, bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p>In Believers Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, there are no Contradictions at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the practice of it.</p>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:154397:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>Believers Baptized come lawfully and immediately to the Lord's Supper, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41, 42.</p>
                  <p>Believers Baptiſm is a ſign of Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration unto them, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5.</p>
                  <p>Believers Baptiſm hath a Command, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18, 19.</p>
                  <p>Believers Baptiſm confirms unto them Juſtification, Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and Salvation, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. Chap. 22.16. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16.</p>
                  <p>We have many Examples for Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Baptiſm, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. Chap. 10. Ch. 16.18.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt was faithful in all his Houſe; and St. <hi>Paul</hi> delivered
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:154397:46"/> the whole Counſel of God, and ſo Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Baptiſm is a part of God's Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.</p>
                  <p>Believers Baptiſm hath been gloriouſly ſealed in the Holy Ghoſt's coming upon Chriſt in the likeneſs of a Dove, when he was coming up out of the Water, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.16.</p>
                  <p>In Believers Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm the Perſon bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized acts Faith, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37.</p>
                  <p>In Believers Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, the Subject bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized hath the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16.</p>
                  <p>A Man might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably die, as many have done in <hi>Mentz, Holland, Germany,</hi> and the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting <hi>Believers Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> becauſe it hath God's Word for its Foundation.</p>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:154397:46"/>
                  <p>The <hi>Publicans</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified God, in being baptized with <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm, becauſe it was the Counſel of God, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Lawyers</hi> rejected the Counſel of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt themſelves, in not being baptized with the Baptiſm of <hi>John,</hi> Luke 3.</p>
                  <p>In Believers Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm there is a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Harmony with the Commiſſion, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.16.</p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:154397:47"/>
                  <p>Believers Baptiſm requireth much Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as according to God's Word, <hi>John</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p>It's without all doubt, Believers were Baptized.</p>
                  <p>To baptize Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, is to keep the Ordinances as they were delivered, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2.</p>
                  <p>To baptize Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, is no change of God's Ordinance.</p>
                  <p>Such as are bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed on their own Faith, ſhall never pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, <hi>John</hi> 10.28.</p>
                  <p>Believers are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized as an Act of their Judgment, Choice, Will and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; ſo worſhip God in Spirit and Truth, <hi>John</hi> 4.24.</p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:154397:47"/>
                  <p>All thoſe who bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize Infants, do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Believers were baptized.</p>
                  <p>Believers know and remember when they were baptized.</p>
                  <p>All Believers bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, are in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace.</p>
                  <p>Believers Baptiſm is from Heaven, and the Counſel of God, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.25.</p>
                  <p>Believers baptized are not the Children of Wrath, <hi>John</hi> 3.36.</p>
                  <p>To baptize Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, is to act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern and Command of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>All Believers bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, receive Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Sins, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p>In Believers Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, the Perſon ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in Acts of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:154397:48"/>
                  <p>Believers Baptiſm hath no Abſurdities attending it.</p>
                  <p>Believers rejoice and ſhew their full Conſent when they are baptized, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.</p>
                  <p>Believers Baptiſm hath the plain Word of God.</p>
                  <p>All the World may affirm, Believers were baptized by the Apoſtles.</p>
                  <p>All Believers bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, are ſpiritual believing Stones, fit to be laid in God's Houſe, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5.</p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:154397:48"/>
                  <p>Believers baptized may repel Satan, as Chriſt did, ſaying, <hi>It is written,</hi> Luke 4.</p>
                  <p>God will not ſay unto Believers bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, <hi>Who hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired theſe things at your Hands?</hi> becauſe it is his own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
                  <p>Believers Baptiſm muſt ſtand as long as God's Word doth ſtand, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.18.</p>
                  <p>To baptize Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, is to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect unto God's Command, the only way not to be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.6.</p>
                  <p>The moſt Holy, the moſt Wiſe, the moſt Learned Perſon that ever was in the World, ſubmitted unto Believers-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.13, 14, 15, 16, 17.</p>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:154397:49"/>
                  <p>Perſons baptized, believe, repent, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine themſelves, make Judgment of things, love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, take up Chriſt's Croſs, Watch and Pray, and have the ſame care of each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Souls; theſe are fit Members of a Goſpel-Church.</p>
                  <p>Believers Baptiſm hath Antiquity to plead, being as old as <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> Chriſt, and his Apoſtles.</p>
                  <p>Believers ought to be baptized, who have an inherent Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs wrought by the Holy Spirit.</p>
                  <p>Believers Baptiſm hath many glorious Promiſes annexed unto it, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38, 39.</p>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:154397:49"/>
                  <p>In Believers Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm all the holy Ends of it are preſerved, as to be a ſign of preſent Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, dying to Sin, bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying, riſing with Chriſt, Anſwer of a good Conſcience; a mutual Stipulation and Contract between God and the Party.</p>
                  <p>In Believers Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, by Dipping, the Manner and true Adminiſtration is preſerved, the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Times retained, and the Ends of it manifeſt.</p>
                  <p>Believers Baptiſm introduceth no Error nor falſe Doctrine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World.</p>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:154397:50"/>
                  <p>Believers baptized are taught of God, and made his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.10.</p>
                  <p>If none ought to forbid the Baptiſm of Water unto thoſe who had been bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed with the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.44, 45, 46, 47, 48.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt ſubmitted unto Water-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:154397:50"/> and ate the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per with his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, who had the Holy Spirit without meaſure.</p>
                  <p>Water-Baptiſm is to continue unto the End of the World, and the Sacrament of the Supper unto the ſecond coming of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20.</p>
                  <p>If Chriſt will have Glory in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches throughout all Ages, World with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end, then he muſt have a Church and Ordinances admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, which is the Eſſence of a Church-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and ſo cannot want Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, becauſe Chriſt hath given Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangeliſts, Paſtors, Teachers,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:154397:51"/> for the perfecting of the Saints, for the Work of the Miniſtry, edifying of the Body of Chriſt: How long? till we all come to the Unity of the Faith, and of the Knowledg of the Son of God, unto a perfect Man, unto the meaſure of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Fulneſs of God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.21. Chap. 4.11, 12.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="epitome">
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:154397:44"/>
                  <head>Infant-Baptiſm.</head>
                  <p>GOD hath not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed all Infants that are Baptized, ſhall be ſaved.</p>
                  <p>But there is no Simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude between Chriſt's Death, Burial, Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and Infants ſprinkled on the Face.</p>
                  <p>But Infants Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed are not converted, and may come into Condemnation.</p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:154397:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>But Infants Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, do not love God, and keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments.</p>
                  <p>Therefore Infant-Baptiſm muſt be of Men, becauſe it's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Teaching, Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Believing.</p>
                  <p>But thoſe who bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize Infants, baptize Heathens; becauſe all are Children of Wrath by Nature before born again, <hi>Epheſ. 3.2.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But Infant-Baptiſm hath manifold Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, by aſſerting that Baptiſm is a Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bol of preſent Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, yet apply it to an ignorant Infant: Alſo that it figures out Chriſt's Death, Burial, and Reſurrection, yet do nothing but ſprinkle, or pour Water on the Face; They ſeparate from <hi>Rome</hi> as the falſe Church, yet own their Baptiſm, the Foundation-Stone; They own the Doctrine of Perſeverance in Grace, and no falling from it, baptizing the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:154397:45"/> Children of Believers as in the Covenant of Grace, yet afterwards teach their Converſion, and in caſe of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief, reject them as Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates.</p>
                  <p>But Infants Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, come not to the Lord's Supper imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately nor lawfully.</p>
                  <p>But the Baptiſm of Infants cannot be a ſign of Regeneration to them.</p>
                  <p>Infant-Baptiſm hath no Command.</p>
                  <p>But Infants have none of thoſe confirmed to them in their Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</p>
                  <p>But we have not one Example for the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing an Infant.</p>
                  <p>But Infant-Baptiſm is no part of God's Counſel, appears, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:154397:46"/> Chriſt nor his Apoſtles never deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered any ſuch thing.</p>
                  <p>Infant Baptiſm ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was ſealed by God.</p>
                  <p>But in Infant-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm the Infant acts no Faith.</p>
                  <p>But Infants have no anſwer of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in Baptiſm.</p>
                  <p>But how can any die for Infant-Baptiſm, when it wants the Broad Seal of God's Word for the Authority?</p>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:154397:46"/>
                  <p>But God is not glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in Infants Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, becauſe none of God's Counſel.</p>
                  <p>But to reject Infant-Baptiſm, cannot be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any Perſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is none of the Counſel of God.</p>
                  <p>But there is no har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion in Infant-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, nor with their own Profeſſion, which is, that Faith and Repentance is required in Perſons to be baptized, yet confeſs that Children, unto whom they apply it, have neither. Again, that it is a demonſtration of a Spiritual Marriage between God and the Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, yet aſſign it unto Subjects as uncapable of it, as a Stock or Stone. Moreover, that the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal Covenant enters into the Viſible Church, yet deny Church-Members the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:154397:47"/>
                  <p>But Infant-Baptiſm needs but a little, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not according to God's Word.</p>
                  <p>But the baptizing Infants at the beſt is doubtful.</p>
                  <p>But it was never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered as an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Chriſt to ſprinkle Infants.</p>
                  <p>But to baptize In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, is to change God's Ordinance in the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and Manner.</p>
                  <p>But ſuch as are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized on anothers Faith, may periſh.</p>
                  <p>Infants cannot wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God in that Act, in Spirit and Truth, becauſe not an Act of Judgment and Choice, Will and Affection.</p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:154397:47"/>
                  <p>But all who baptize Believers, do deny that Infants were baptized.</p>
                  <p>Infants know not, remember not any thing of their Baptiſm.</p>
                  <p>All Infants bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, are not in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace.</p>
                  <p>Infants Baptiſm is from Earth, and the Counſel of Men.</p>
                  <p>But Infants bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed may be Children of Wrath.</p>
                  <p>But to baptize In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, is to act with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Pattern or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
                  <p>But all Infants bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, do not receive Remiſſion of Sins.</p>
                  <p>But in Infants Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, the Infant puts forth no Act of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:154397:48"/>
                  <p>But Infants Baptiſm hath many, namely, that Perſons may have Regeneration &amp; Grace before Vocation; and that Perſons may be viſible Church-Members before Converſion. Moreover, that Perſons may be baptized by another's Faith. Alſo making a National Goſpel-Church inſtead of a Congregational; and bringing in a carnal fleſhly Seed into Chriſt's Church, in the room of a Spiritual Seed.</p>
                  <p>But Infants weep when baptized, as if they did diſſent.</p>
                  <p>Infant-Baptiſm hath nothing but humane Conſequence.</p>
                  <p>But all the World cannot affirm any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants were baptized by the Apoſtles.</p>
                  <p>But all Infants bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, are not living Stones fit for God's Houſe.</p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:154397:48"/>
                  <p>But you cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Satan, ſaying, <hi>It is written,</hi> Infants were baptized, for it is not written.</p>
                  <p>But God may ſay to thoſe who baptize In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, <hi>Who hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired theſe things at your Hands?</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God commanded it not.</p>
                  <p>But Infant-Baptiſm muſt fall, becauſe it hath not the Word of God to ſupport it.</p>
                  <p>But to baptize In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, without a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Command, is the way to be made aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, becauſe no reſpect to God's Command.</p>
                  <p>But the moſt Holy, the moſt Wiſe, the moſt Learned, never was ſubjected unto Infant-Baptiſm.</p>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:154397:49"/>
                  <p>But Infants bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, cannot repent or believe, examine themſelves, make no Judgment of things, nor take up Chriſt's Croſs, Watch nor Pray, love not, nor watch not over one another, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Members of a Goſpel-Church.</p>
                  <p>Infant-Baptiſm hath ſtarted up ſeveral hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years ſince Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</p>
                  <p>But Infants ought not to be baptized, who are only legitimately Holy, as all born in Wedlock are; and is the Holineſs mentioned <hi>1 Cor. 7.14.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Infant-Baptiſm hath not one Promiſe.</p>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:154397:49"/>
                  <p>But in Infant-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm all theſe are fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, and being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to an Infant, are but Mock-ſhows, and altogether inſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant.</p>
                  <p>But Infant-Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, is an inverting the Order and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and contrary to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick Times, and End of the Ordinance; and is a telling a Lie in the Name of the Lord, ſaying, <hi>I Baptize,</hi> when he doth but Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize.</p>
                  <p>But Infant-Baptiſme doth introduce many Errors, in that it was to take away Original Sin, work Grace and Regeneration, effect Salvation by the Work
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:154397:50"/> done; that it was an Apoſtolical Tradition; that Children have Faith, and are Diſciples of Chriſt; that all Children of Believers are in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, defiling and polluting the Church with falſe Matter, and confounding the Church and the World together; introducing many hainous Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and Inventions of Antichriſt together with it, as Goſſips or Sureties, Biſhoping or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, Chriſm, Exorciſm, Conſignation. Laſtly, It hath made a great deal of Contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Church of Chriſt, and ſtirred up much Hatred.</p>
                  <p>Infants baptized are not taught of God, nor made Diſciples of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Then ſuch are great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Heterodox and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound, who ſlight and contemn Water-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, under pretence of being baptized with the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>Then that Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is of Fleſh, and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:154397:50"/> not Spirit, of Man, and not God, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects Water-Baptiſm, and the Supper, as car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, under an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded imagination of the Baptiſm of the Spirit.</p>
                  <p>Then for any to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect thoſe Ordinances under an imagination thoſe Commands cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at the end of the Apoſtles Age, are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a deluſion.</p>
                  <p>If ſo, then the Church-State did not end with the Apoſtles, neither can Ordinances ceaſe for want of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrators.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:154397:51"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Contains an Enquiry into the Carriages of the <hi>German Anabaptiſts</hi> (falſly ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) in <hi>Luther</hi>'s Time, and the Reproach from thence reflected upon that Way re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved.</head>
               <p>THE Matter of Fact which hath cauſed ſuch a Noiſe in the World about the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Perſons, in the Year 1520, is as follows.</p>
               <p>There was a Conſpiracy of Husbandmen againſt the Biſhop and Canons; which began from two Ruſticks, hence called <hi>the Clowns and Ruſtick War.</hi> The principal Article was, That they ſhould ſhake off every Yoke, for their Exactions and Oppreſſions were very great; ſome did pay more Rent yearly to their Lords, than their Farms were worth. And albeit the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:154397:52"/> Boors pleaded firſt for their Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Liberties, yet after cried up for Goſpel-Liberty, as appears from <hi>Luther</hi>'s Admonition and Reprehenſion of them, for uſing the Sword to obtain it. It may be ſuppoſed, many of them knew very little of the Goſpel, though others might; but both Papiſts and Proteſtants conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt the Cruelty of their Lords.</p>
               <p>Hence you have <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi>'s words; <q>Some are called Princes, but are indeed Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants; they care not for you, they take your Goods, and ſpend them wickedly in Pride and Riot: And for light Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes make Wars, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all the Poor have left. In the place of Widows and Orphans, they maintain the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi>'s Authority, and Wickedneſs of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy. Where Youth ſhould be brought up in Learning, and the Poor relieved, they eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the Merchandize of Maſſing, and other Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations.
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:154397:52" rendition="simple:additions"/> Think you God will ſuffer theſe any longer? we ought rather to die, than to allow their Wickedneſs, and ſuffer the Doctrine of the Goſpel to be taken from us.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> confeſs'd much of this to be true; and largely admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed Magiſtrates to their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, tho he reproved them who made the Inſurrection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philip</hi> Landgrave of <hi>Heſſe,</hi> did confeſs the things they were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of were true, and many things ought to be amended, yet ſaid, It was not lawful to riſe againſt their Prince, unto whom God had given the Sword. But we know, <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, <hi>makes a wiſe Man mad,</hi> eſpecially when Civil and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Liberties are invaded.</p>
               <p>How few good People con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the Undertaking of the Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> when he came to deliver us from Popery and Slavery?</p>
               <p>Very few good People but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice in our preſent Condition,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:154397:53"/> tho won by the Sword. The <hi>Switzers,</hi> their Neighbours, had done the like before, and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded: And had <hi>Geneva</hi> miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carried, or any of the famous Men among the <hi>Cantons,</hi> they and their Religion might have fallen under as much Obloquy. And had the Church of <hi>England</hi> miſcarried in the bringing in our preſent King, (whom God cauſe long to reign) no People would have been under greater Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach in the World, by ſome ſort of Men, though done to preſerve their Civil and Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Liberties out of the Hands of Papiſts.</p>
               <p>The things the <hi>Munſterians</hi> demanded, were,</p>
               <p n="1">1. To have liberty to chuſe ſuch Preachers as might preach God's Word, without mixture of Mens Traditions.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Pay no Tithes but of Corn only, and the ſame to be diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted according to the diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of good Men.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They refuſe not to obey a Magiſtrate, knowing that he is
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:154397:53"/> ordained of God, but cannot endure to be kept in Bonds, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be ſhewed reaſonable in Scripture.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Eaſed of theſe Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, becauſe ſome did pay more Rent yearly unto their Lords than their Farms were worth.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That thoſe things which were not a particular Man's Property, might be free, for Building, Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, Hunting, Fiſhing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Papiſts to this day do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon the whole Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Calvin, Luther, Zuing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> &amp;c. upon as good grounds as the Proteſtants have ſince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected upon the Baptiſts, becauſe ſeveral of their Perſwaſion were concern'd in that Attempt for Freedom; as 'tis well known many good Men, of moſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Presbyterians, Independents, Baptiſts,</hi> were zealouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the D. of <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s Time, and many fell, as thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of thoſe did in <hi>Weſtphalia.</hi> But know, Victory is no Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the beſt Cauſe, nor beſt
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:154397:54"/> Men, nor a Defeat an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a bave Cauſe, and bad Men; for God's own Church and People have fled often be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Infidels.</hi> Love nor Hatred is known by External Providences, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9. Many times it fares with the Wicked as the Godly, and with the Godly as the Wicked, in outward things, as Divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom pleaſeth. No better Men in the World, than ſome which fell in the Duke's Cauſe in the Weſt, yet by the hands of one of the moſt debauched Armies that ever was in the World: And if we think to know theſe things, they are too wonderful for us, as they were for <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 73.16.</p>
               <p>And as to thoſe horrible Things which are ſaid to have been in the City of <hi>Munſter</hi> in <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> from the Year 1532, to 1536. by <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Matthias Gnipper-doling;</hi> it is manifeſt, from ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Authors, that the firſt ſtir in that City was about the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:154397:54"/> Reformation, the Synod ſiding with Mr. <hi>Rotomon,</hi> and others of the Miniſters who were for the Reformation, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Papiſts, and their Biſhops and Canons. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden, Jo. Matthias,</hi> and <hi>Jo. Becold</hi> came after this Inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on began.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> by Arguments had made Mr. <hi>Rotomon,</hi> who was for Pedobaptiſm, a Proſelyte for Believers-Baptiſm, and died in that Cauſe in <hi>Munſter.</hi> He by Preaching brought over a great part of the City to own this Principle. He ſent Letters to the <hi>Landgrave,</hi> and a Book of his Doctrine; which <hi>Luther</hi> op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and he oppoſed <hi>Luther</hi> as he did the Bp. of <hi>Rome:</hi> And it was no wonder <hi>Luther</hi> oppoſed him, who died in the practice of Pedobaptiſm.</p>
               <p>And whereas 'tis reported, that monſtrous Wickedneſs was committed in the latter part of the Siege, before they were overcome. We have good
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:154397:55"/> ground to queſtion the Truth thereof; Firſt, Becauſe <hi>Sleiden</hi> in his Comment, who repreſents the Matter as unhandſom as he could, doth confeſs Mr. <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer</hi> did preach againſt open crying Sins, as Murder, Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, blaſpheming God's Name, the Body chaſtened and made lean with Faſting, ſimple Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, Countenance grave, ſpeak ſeldom, get much out of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, think oft of God, what he is, what Care he has over us, whether Chriſt died for our Sins, whether our Religion be better than the <hi>Turks.</hi> Moreover, to ask of God a Sign whereby he may teſtify his Care for us, and that we be in the true Religion; and though he ſhew no Token for Good quickly, yet muſt we nevertheleſs proceed in Prayer, yea, expoſtulate with God, ſeeing the Scripture promiſeth, <hi>he will grant what we ask.</hi> Theſe good things may make us doubt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome other Principles and Practices he writes of, which are
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:154397:55"/> contrary to thoſe things, were true.</p>
               <p>Moreover, we have good reaſon to queſtion theſe Reports, if we conſider further that thoſe things were either written by malicious <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who ſaid as bad of <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting them no leſs Monſters; who aſſerted that <hi>Luther</hi> and his Followers taught, that <hi>Mary</hi> the Mother of Chriſt had more Sons, &amp; that the youngeſt, <hi>James</hi> an Apoſtle, died for us, and not Chriſt himſelf. Or theſe things were written by ſome diſaffected <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> who were willing to take up and improve ſuch Reports, to blaſt, not only the Parties Reputation, but their Principle alſo. And one thing which cauſed this People, called <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> to be miſrepreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, was, their Community of Goods which they alway had at <hi>Munſter,</hi> which was no other than the old <hi>Waldenſes</hi> did, and their Diſciples do to this day, in <hi>Poland, Hungary, Tranſylvania,</hi>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:154397:56"/> and many parts of <hi>Germany,</hi> living in Colledges, caſting all into one Common Stock, done by them, both from Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, and having reſpect unto the Example of the Apoſtles and Primitive Chriſtians, as it is written in <hi>Acts</hi> 4.32, 34, 35. And though we do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve Chriſtians are now under that Obligation, yet I cannot have a hard thought of any that ſhould ſo do, acting from the ſame Primitive Spirit: And it would be very unchriſtian to conclude, that ſuch allow a Community of Women, becauſe they had their Stock and Goods in common, as I fear ſome have uncharitably aſſerted, from this innocent Apoſtolical Primitive Practice.</p>
               <p>To conclude; Suppoſe it ſhould be granted there were ſome fooliſh Virgins in <hi>Germany,</hi> under this Denomination of <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> it is no more than what Chriſt hath told us will
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:154397:56"/> be. Have not the Churches in all Ages had their <hi>Achan's, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah's, Dathan's, Abiram's,</hi> their <hi>Diotrephaes?</hi> But is it good Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick to ſay, <hi>Judas</hi> had a Devil, therefore all the Apoſtles had Devils? Hath there not been always ſome bad in the moſt pure Churches of Chriſt? For any to ſay there are no good Men, nor good Principles in the Communion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe ſome of that Communion are Executed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt every Seſſions, as they confeſs themſelves to be at <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn,</hi> this would be unjuſt and uncharitable: And it argueth weakneſs for any to run upon Extreams, becauſe of others Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors. As ſome of the Miniſters in <hi>Holland,</hi> the Followers of <hi>Meno Symonis,</hi> and <hi>Theodori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> upon the <hi>Munſter</hi> Report, have refuſed the bearing Arms, Offenſive or Defenſive; or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any Oaths, or bearing any Rule, Office, or Government in the Common-Wealth, leſt
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:154397:57"/> they ſhould ſeem to abet ſuch Principles: It is good to keep the golden Mean between both Extreams.</p>
               <p>Now let us all labour to put on Charity, the Bond of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; think no Evil, nor ſpeak Evil of no Man; <hi>Judg not, that ye be not judged: Why doſt thou judg thy Brother, or ſet at naught thy Brother? We ſhall all ſtand before the Judgment-Seat of Chriſt.</hi> Let that great Inſtance of Deſpair in <hi>John Child</hi> never be forgotten; that which lay with the moſt weight upon his Conſcience, before he hang'd himſelf, was, the Sin for his Writing and Speaking againſt this very People, as may be ſeen in that Book of his Deſpair. And thoſe Scriptures were of great weight upon his Soul; <hi>He that offends one of theſe little Ones which believe in me, it were better a Mill-ſtone were hanged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his Neck, and he caſt into the midst of the Sea. O,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>I
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:154397:57"/> have touched the Apple of God's Eye: and,</hi> ſays he, <hi>this deſerves a tearing in pieces, to ſit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſpeak againſt thy Brother, and ſlander thy own Mother's Son,</hi> Pſal. 50.</p>
               <p>Let all the People of God have ſuch Thoughts, ſpeak ſuch Words, uſe ſuch Carriages one toward another, and one of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, as we may have no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to repent of, when every ſecret Thing ſhall be brought into Judgment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:154397:58"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Containing a brief but ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Anſwer to <hi>John Wall</hi>'s Book, called <hi>Baptiſm Anatomized,</hi> that he may never more boaſt, as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, that none have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him.</head>
               <p>I Query, 1. Whether this Man doth not act againſt the Light of Conſcience, Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and Holy Scripture, when he aſſerts indefinitely, <hi>The Infants of Believers have, by the free Gift of God in the Covenant of Grace, a right to Remiſſion of Sins, and ſo a right to Baptiſm?</hi> Come and ſtand before the Bar of God's Word, and make anſwer, Had <hi>Cain, Iſhmael, Eſau, Abſolom, Samuel</hi>'s Sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> all Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Believers, a right to Remiſſion of Sins?</p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:154397:58"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Query</hi> 2. Whether there is not good ground given unto Perſons to believe, (in reading a great part of this Book, from <hi>pag.</hi> 25, to 41, &amp; 168.) that he is of <hi>Origen</hi>'s Opinion, The whole World may be ſaved at laſt, and then why not the Devils too? <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he, <hi>pag.</hi> 168.) <hi>if all Infants ſinned in</hi> Adam<hi>'s Loins, when</hi> Adam <hi>was reſtored, they were reſtored in his Loins; and when born, they were born in a Goſpel-Covenant.</hi> In <hi>Pag.</hi> 26. <hi>God free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forgave</hi> Adam <hi>and his Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in him, their Sin. Now we know the whole World is</hi> Adam<hi>'s Children, then the whole World is in the Covenant of Grace, and ſo the whole muſt be baptized; and if in the Covenant of Grace, for any thing I ſee, the whole World may be ſaved.</hi> Abundance of theſe Aſſertions he hath in his Book. But behold, it is a <hi>Babel,</hi> a Book of Confuſion; for though he tells us, when the Parents be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, <hi>pag.</hi> 27, 28. their Baptiſm is a ſign of the Remiſſion of Sin to their Infants as to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:154397:59"/> and that their Infants are in the Covenant of Grace with them, it being made to <hi>Adam</hi> and his Poſterity. Yet <hi>Cain, Iſhmael, Eſau,</hi> he aſſerts were caſt out of this Covenant of Grace when grown up, and have no Remiſſion of Sins. What, have Believers Infants Remiſſion ſealed unto them, yet no Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion? Will Men tell a Lie in the Name of the Lord, to tell us, that Baptiſm is a ſign of Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Sin, and yet to tell us, this very Perſon may be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? Are not theſe Self-contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, and holy Scripture-contradictions, which ſaith, <hi>Whom God juſtifieth and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doneth, them he glorifieth?</hi> Rom. 8.30. In my Book this is more fully anſwered, <hi>pag.</hi> 29.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Query</hi> 3. Whether his Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage favours not more of <hi>Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dod</hi> than <hi>Canaan?</hi> and whether it be not full of hard Speeches againſt thoſe which <hi>John Child</hi> paid dearly for, and of whom Chriſt ſaith, <hi>It were better a Mill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone were tied about his Neck, and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:154397:59"/> he caſt into the midst of the Sea?</hi> For in his Preface, he accounts the Miniſters of Chriſt, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Satan transform'd, to deceive the Souls of the Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And in <hi>pag.</hi> 3. falſly ſaith, if not maliciouſly, <hi>The Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts deny Infants to be redeemed with Chriſt's Blood, p.</hi> 31. And <hi>p.</hi> 55. he ſaith, <hi>The Anabaptiſts hold, Chriſt hath no Lambs in his Fold, but all Sheep,</hi> becauſe we will not own Pedobaptiſm. And <hi>pag.</hi> 65. <hi>What a wicked Principle are thoſe Men of that deny Infants the ſign of Remiſſion of Sins, and that we make an Idol of Baptiſm,</hi> is his Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And becauſe we aſſert, Chriſt was baptized about thirty Years of Age, as our Example; <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>what windings and turnings, by any cover of vain deceit, Men lie in wait to deceive, by turning away from the Truth, and turning unto Fables.</hi> And further ſaith, <hi>pag.</hi> 10. <hi>We hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritically plead for that we pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe not.</hi> Whether this Man's Diſcourſe favours as being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Power of a divine, or
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:154397:60"/> diabolical Spirit, is left to the Godly to judg; and whether any heed ought to be taken of ſuch a Perſon's Writing.</p>
               <p>In <hi>pag.</hi> 139. he aſſerts, <hi>We damn the Infants of all God's Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of old by our Doctrine.</hi> And enviouſly addeth, <hi>pag.</hi> 171. <hi>The Anabaptiſts are not only erroneous in their Faith, and there polluted,</hi> but alſo garniſhed with ſhame to Nature, in <hi>pag.</hi> 169. calling our Faith, <hi>a Carnal Faith.</hi> I think, were he a Spiritual Man, he could not have ſuch carnal Language. O, how far is this poor Man from imitating our Lord, <hi>When he was reviled, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viled not again:</hi> But this Man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viles when no occaſion is given him. But he hath not yet ſpit all his Venom, for in <hi>pag.</hi> 71. he ſaith, <hi>The Anabaptiſts Doctrine is not of God, but a Point of their natural Faith.</hi> And further ſaith, <hi>Theſe Men are ſenſual, having not the Spirit,</hi> calling us <hi>Beaſts; pag.</hi> 111. And <hi>that we make Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood our Refuge.</hi> And <hi>pag.</hi> 117. ſaith, <hi>Chriſt hath preſerved the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:154397:60"/> Infant-Seed of Believers from the Curſe of Anabaptiſtry, whereby ſo many Errors are diſperſed, Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures wreſted, &amp; Souls perverted to their own deſtruction. Pag.</hi> 143. he aſſerts the Doctrine upon which Anabaptiſtry is built, is <hi>a Soul-deſtroying Doctrine;</hi> and that we have belied the Lord's Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, although we repeated no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but their own Words, and that, ſaith he, to uphold our Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, <hi>pag.</hi> 116. And cries out, <hi>pag.</hi> 66. as well he might, if true, <hi>The Anabaptiſts reckon their own Children dying in Infancy, by their own judgment loſt, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh to Eternity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pray conſider, Is not this Man's Doctrine agreeable with the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>'s, and the Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> who decre'd, <hi>If any aſſerted Baptiſm did not take away Original Sin, they ſhould be Anathematized?</hi> Is this reaſoning like a Man, or Chriſtian? Becauſe we dare not in Conſcience give the Sacrament of Baptiſm to our Infants, muſt they be damned therefore? We can tell you a
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:154397:61"/> better way of waſhing away of Original Sin, namely, by the Imputation of Chriſt's Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, to Infants dying in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy.</p>
               <p>My Prayer ſhall be, <hi>John Wall,</hi> for thee, that thou mayeſt not run the hazard of thy Soul (as <hi>John Child</hi> did) ſo thou mayeſt but reproach the Innocent Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God. But as if all this were not yet enough, he aſſerts, <hi>Our Baptiſm is not from Heaven, but Will-worſhip, and ſo to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred of all Chriſtians: for,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>they received their Baptiſm from one Mr.</hi> Smith, <hi>who baptized him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> pag. 106, 107, 108. <hi>one who was caſt out of a Church, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to deprive the Church of Chriſt of the uſe of the Bible.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O full of all Subtilty, and all Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief!</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 3.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Enemy of Righteouſneſs,</hi> (for the <hi>Ordinance</hi> is ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) <hi>when wilt thou ceaſe to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the right Ways of the Lord?</hi> How many Leaves haſt thou ſpent in thy Book, in aſſerting and maintaining a Lie, and to caſt Filth upon the holy Ways
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:154397:61"/> of the Lord? Could not the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Chriſt, which was loſt in the Apoſtacy, be revived, (as the Feaſt of Tabernacles was, tho loſt a great while) unleſs in ſuch a filthy way as you falſly aſſert, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>the Engliſh Baptiſts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived their Baptiſm from Mr.</hi> John Smith? It is abſolutely untrue, it being well known, by ſome yet alive, how falſe this Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is; and if <hi>J. W.</hi> will but give a meeting to any of us, and bring whom he pleaſeth with him, we ſhall ſufficiently ſhew the Falſity of what is affirmed by him in this Matter, and in many other things he hath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianly aſſerted.</p>
               <p>Mark, his ſecond Query is, <hi>What is the End of Baptiſm?</hi> Pag. 22. ſaith he, <hi>John, ſirnamed the Baptiſt, hath ſhewed the End in the Sign, why Water-Baptiſm was ordained; namely, it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, that Chriſt ſhould be made manifeſt to</hi> Iſrael; <hi>and for the waſhing away of Sins, Remiſſion of Sins; and that Chriſt the Lamb of God is now come, according to
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:154397:62"/> the Goſpel-Promiſe,</hi> Gen. 3.15.</p>
               <p>We anſwer, All theſe things are very good Ends in the Sign, to an underſtanding Believer who can take the comfort of it. But what comfort can an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Infant take in Chriſt's being manifeſted in the Sign, or of Chriſt being come, or of the Pardon and Remiſſion of Sin? theſe things <hi>are Meat for ſtrong Men, not for Babes:</hi> anſwered more fully, <hi>pag.</hi> 23, 24.</p>
               <p>In <hi>pag.</hi> 4. of his Preface, he ſaith, <hi>We ground our Doctrine on Nature, and plead a right to Goſpel-Ordinances by the Act of Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We anſwer, We never un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood that we grounded our Doctrine upon Nature, but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Will of God revealed in the Goſpel: And for our plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for a right to Goſpel-Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances by Mens Actions; if you will call <hi>Repentance</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> Mens Actions, you may in ſome good ſenſe; for though God give Faith, 'tis not God's Act to believe, but Man's; though God give Repentance, it is not God's
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:154397:62"/> Act to repent, but Man's: And if Perſons are offended becauſe we require what Chriſt requires as prerequiſite to Baptiſm; if that be to be vile, we muſt be ſtill ſo.</p>
               <p>He would inſinuate, <hi>pag.</hi> 3. that in Baptiſm a Perſon is wholly paſſive, becauſe he is ſo in the Baptiſm of the Spirit and of Afflictions. But ſhall we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve God or Man? Chriſt ſaith, He muſt be active in the Grace of Faith and Repentance. <hi>Paul</hi> muſt be active, and ariſe to the Ordinance. Chriſt was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive in going into <hi>Jordan,</hi> and coming up; ſo the <hi>Eunuch</hi> went down into the Water, as an Act of his Judgment, Will, and Affection; both Soul and Body is active in this Ordinance: How then is Man wholly paſſive in Baptiſm?</p>
               <p>In the laſt Page of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face he nicknames the Intereſt of God, calling them <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> or <hi>Rebaptizers; yet,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>it is no Nickname.</hi> Which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed muſt be, 1. becauſe we own
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:154397:63"/> but one Baptiſm, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.5. 2. Perſons in Infancy are not <hi>Baptized,</hi> but <hi>Rantized,</hi> therefore 'tis no Rebaptizing. 3. Should it be ſaid Children were Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, yet it was no proper Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Baptiſm, becauſe it wanted a proper Subject; it was an ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Infant, inſtead of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding Believer. 4. If <hi>John</hi> was called <hi>John the Baptiſt,</hi> becauſe he baptized Perſons up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on profeſſion of Repentance, and Faith in him who was to come after him; why may not thoſe be ſo called that follow his Practice, tho they have no extraordinary Commiſſion as he had? What is more common, than to call them by the ſame Name of thoſe whoſe Principle and Practice they approve of; and that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently enough, as <hi>Calviniſts</hi> from <hi>Calvin, Lutherans</hi> from <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi> ſo we own the word of <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> becauſe we are in the ſame Faith and Practice with <hi>John the Baptiſt,</hi> Chriſt's Harbin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. So that it plainly appears, 'tis a Nickname, and a Name of
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:154397:63"/> Reproach caſt upon thoſe of this Perſwaſion. Turn to Page 64 and 65 for a fuller Anſwer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 4, 5. he will have Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm to be a pouring of Water upon the Face, becauſe 'tis ſaid, <hi>God will pour out of his Spirit upon his.</hi> By way of anſwer, he is to know, <hi>pouring</hi> was the moſt proper word could be uſed for the Holy Spirit's proceeding, becauſe it is Above, with God in Heaven, and we upon Earth below; but the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Water is beneath us, for Men go down into the Sea. So accordingly it was practiſed in the Apoſtles Time, they went down <hi>into</hi> the Water; which if it had not been to be dipp'd in it, they need to have gone only <hi>unto</hi> it: therefore, how vain is that he aſſerts, <hi>John</hi> baptized ſtanding at the brink of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Jordan, pag.</hi> 8. This is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict the Word of God, which ſaith plainly, <hi>Philip</hi> and the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch</hi> went both down into the Water (not to the brink of it) and came up out of the Water.</p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:154397:64"/>
               <p>In <hi>pag.</hi> 4, <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. his great Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, by which he thinks to do the moſt Execution, is from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.1, 2. where it is ſaid, <hi>All our Fathers were baptized unto</hi> Moſes <hi>in the Cloud, and in the Sea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer,</hi> 1. Conſider, it is ſaid, the Fathers, not the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, were baptized. 2. If you will have it the Children alſo, then you muſt include there, Beaſts and Cattel, for the Cloud poured Water upon them all. 3. Where-ever the word Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is uſed, whether it be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the Spirit, to Sufferings, or to Water, it always ſheweth ſome large meaſure of all. So here they were baptized in the Cloud, and in the Sea; not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly baptized, for that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance was not in uſe then, but the ſcope of that place is, the Apoſtle thought fit to borrow that word <hi>Baptize,</hi> for to ſhow <hi>God</hi>'s gracious protection of them in the <hi>Red-Sea;</hi> as in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs he fed them with <hi>Manna from Heaven,</hi> and gave them Water
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:154397:64"/> out of a Rock: So he left them not in the Red-Sea, but encompaſſed them about in ſafety, by his Divine Providence, with Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter on each ſide of them, and the Cloud over them, as Perſons are encompaſſed with that Element when baptized. Again, for the true underſtanding of the Word, we muſt have recourſe to the common Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of it, and not imagine the Spirit of God doth contradict the common Accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Words among Men. When the Prophets wrote by Inſpiration, and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, they always uſed ſuch words as were vulgar, and commonly accepted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Men; ſo that the common accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Hebrew word <hi>Tabal</hi> among the Hebrews, and <hi>Baptizo</hi> among the Greeks, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſignifying <hi>to dip,</hi> there being other words to ſignify <hi>ſprinkle</hi> or <hi>pour.</hi> How then can pouring Rain from the Cloud be called <hi>Baptiſm?</hi> as <hi>John Wall</hi> would needs have it, though he beg for it, becauſe it can never be proved; ſee my Book <hi>pag.</hi> 16, 17.</p>
               <p>And is he not full of audacity or boldneſs to tell the World, in <hi>pag.</hi> 8. <hi>That there is not one word that any by</hi> John <hi>or</hi> Philip <hi>were dipped,</hi> when the very word properly ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth <hi>dipping?</hi> Hence the <hi>Dutch</hi> call <hi>John the Dooper.</hi> And our Tranſlators might as well have rendred <hi>baptize, dip,</hi> in all the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:154397:65"/> where it is, as to render <hi>Judas ſopt, dipp'd; and Chriſt's Veſture dipp'd in Blood,</hi> being all from the ſame Original Word.</p>
               <p>And whereas he tells the World, <hi>pag.</hi> 16, 17. <hi>Though the Scripture ſay, they baptized in</hi> Aenon, <hi>becauſe there was much Water.</hi> He ſaith, <hi>It would not be enough to dip half the Body in.</hi> 1. I ſuppoſe he never was there to ſee it, but ſpeaks by an implicit Faith. 2. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe directs us to believe there was need of much Water to the due perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of that Ordinance, or elſe the Holy Spirit would not have mentioned it as <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious for that Work, becauſe much Water there;</hi> a little Water will ſprinkle hundreds, but much Water is neceſſary unto the due performance of this Ordinance of Baptiſm, becauſe it muſt be ſo done, as to figure out the Death, Burial, and Reſurrection of Chriſt. Now I would fain know, how ſprinkling, or pouring Water upon the Face, doth figure out Chriſt's Death, Burial, and Reſurrection? <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.1, 2, 4.</p>
               <p>In <hi>pag.</hi> 9. how diſingenuouſly doth he deal with <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.12. <hi>We are buried with Chriſt in Baptiſm. To follow their natural Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Perſon buried, is wholly paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, and muſt be taken in Arms, laid upon the Water, then Water caſt upon him, till co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, as Earth is upon the Dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:154397:65"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer,</hi> This way of diſcourſe is a kind of trifling with God's Word. You are to know, Similitudes do not run upon all four, as we ſay, but reſpect muſt alway be had to the chief intent and deſign of a Metaphor, which in this Text is to hold forth the Death, Burial, and Reſurrection of Chriſt, for our Juſtification; and alſo holds forth our Death to Sin, and Reſurrection to a new Life. This being the prime ſcope of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, his way of diſcourſe is nothing but to evade the ſtrength of the Argument.</p>
               <p>Whereas in <hi>pag.</hi> 10. he ſaith, <hi>The Perſon baptizeth part of himſelf, becauſe he goeth into the Water.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We anſwer, That is falſe, becauſe he doth not lay himſelf down in the Water, but that is done by the Adminiſtrator, he lays him along, as one buried under the Water, his whole Body, not the upper part only, to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure out Chriſt's lying in the Grave: for as the Perſons ſtands upright in the Water, that is not Baptiſm, but when laid along un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Water, by the Adminiſtrator, uſing the words of Inſtitution, <hi>I baptize thee in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt,</hi> this is Baptiſm.</p>
               <p>In <hi>pag.</hi> 14. he ſaith, <hi>The Perſon is not bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, but his Cloaths.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe things are not becoming Modeſty
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:154397:66"/> to diſcourſe of; Let that vain Man know, we do not baptize the Cloaths in the Name of the Bleſſed Trinity, but the Perſon; and ſhould we baptize otherwiſe I fear this poor Man would be the firſt would reproach the Intereſt of Chriſt upon that account.</p>
               <p>Whereas he chargeth <hi>B. K. pag.</hi> 80. with the whole Aſſembly of Baptized Believers, that they were forced to try their Wits, for want of thoſe literal words, <hi>Remember you keep holy the First Day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Our Arguments for obſerving the Firſt Day, do greatly ſatisfy our Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, being grounded upon the Word of God. Alſo our Arguments againſt Pedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſm, and for Believers Baptiſm alſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proved from the ſame Divine Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But alas, how are Men put at their Wits end, to find Arguments for Pedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſm? or elſe they would never prefer a dark Conſequence before a plain Command, which is beneath the Reaſon of a Man; nor run to the Law to prove a Goſpel-Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and reject God's Inſtitution, and ſet up Man's Invention. Could he ſay as much for Pedobaptiſm, as we can for the Lord's Day, the Controverſy would not have held ſo long. Could he give us ſuch Examples of Infant-Baptiſm, as we can for our religious obſerving that Day, we ſhall give him thanks.</p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:154397:66"/>
               <p>And whereas in <hi>pag.</hi> 104. he quarrels, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we do not Baptize always upon the Firſt Day. We do not judg we are confin'd to that Day. The Lord's Supper, Chriſt himſelf did inſtitute it, and practiſe it with his Apoſtles, on another Day than the Firſt Day of the Week.</p>
               <p>Although we do grant it is very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable to do ſuch Work on ſuch Days, when retired from our Labour, yet we do not think we are confin'd to that Day; for in the late Perſecution, the Churches of Chriſt, ſome of them, did find it very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to break Bread upon a Week-Day, yet we alway think it beſt on the Firſt, when it may be. And as for Baptiſm, we do not find the Apoſtles tarried for the Revolution of the Firſt Day, but as occaſion offered they did it upon any Day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 69. he inſiſts upon the order of words, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. <hi>I baptize to Repentance.</hi> See this anſwered in my Book, <hi>p.</hi> 54, 55, 56.</p>
               <p>That is a falſe Argument he ſo largely inſiſted on, <hi>pag.</hi> 44. <hi>If Perſons have a right to Remiſſion of Sin, they have a right to the Sign, Baptiſm.</hi> This Argument I have hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in <hi>p.</hi> 36.</p>
               <p>Infants are not called Diſciples, as he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth <hi>pag.</hi> 43. from <hi>Acts</hi> 15.10. and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Requeſt, we will ſhew him a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:154397:67"/> and Example for Womens communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating at the Lord's Table, <hi>p.</hi> 42, 43.</p>
               <p>For anſwer to <hi>pag.</hi> 21. where it's aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>That many of the</hi> 3000 <hi>whom the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles batized in</hi> Acts 2.39. <hi>were Children, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Pardon of Sin was by the Apoſtle</hi> Peter <hi>applied to their Children.</hi> O horrible perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Word of God! theſe Children whom he ſpeaks of, were no more (as yet) baptized, than the Gentiles, which were afar off uncalled. 2. Suppoſe ſome of their Children were baptized, it muſt be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Children, not Infants; my Child is my Child, though thirty or forty Years old, for you cannot think the Apoſtle would go beyond his Commiſſion, to baptize an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Infant in the room of an underſtanding Believer. O how ſophiſtically doth this Man reaſon! ſee <hi>pag.</hi> 29, 30, 31. of this Book.</p>
               <p>Laſtly; I refer you to Mr. <hi>Cary</hi>'s <hi>Solemn Call,</hi> which clears up the Covenant made with <hi>Iſrael</hi> at <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> Exod. 19.20. and that in the Land of <hi>Moab,</hi> Deut. 29. as alſo the Covenant of Circumciſion made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 17. are plainly proved to be three ſeveral Editions of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Works: Though Mr. <hi>Wall</hi> will have it to be a Covenant of Grace in Chriſt. And though he ſpends many Leaves of his
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:154397:67"/> Book about it, 'tis as far from being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as Believers-Baptiſm is a Sign to the Infant of the Remiſſion of Sins, and being in the Covenant of Grace, which yet is confeſt, a few Years after, he is neither in the Covenant of Grace, nor yet one Sin pardoned. Theſe are ſome of this poor Man's Self-contradictions; is he not <hi>Felo de ſe,</hi> a Self-deſtroyer?</p>
               <p>Whereas he ſaith, <hi>pag.</hi> 117. Mr. <hi>Ainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi>'s Book called, <hi>A Cenſure upon a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of the Anabaptists,</hi> was never anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>That in</hi> Abraham<hi>'s Seed all Nations ſhould be bleſſed: This Grace</hi> Abraham<hi>'s Infant-Seed had; this Grace Chriſt gave to little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi> See your ſelf and Mr. <hi>Ainſworth</hi> both anſwered, in <hi>pag.</hi> 37, 38. and <hi>p.</hi> 34, 35.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:154397:68"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> A brief Anſwer to a part of Mr. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel Williams</hi>'s Catechiſm, in his Book of the <hi>Vanity of Childhood and Youth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN <hi>pag.</hi> 131. he propounds theſe Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; What if a Child will not agree, but refuſe to agree to the Covenant to which his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm engaged him?</p>
               <p>Himſelf makes this aſtoniſhing Anſwer.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>It's a rejecting Christ our Saviour, and a renouncing the Bleſſings of the Goſpel.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>It's the Damning Sin.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>It's the Heart of all Sin.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>It's Rebellion continued againſt my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>It's Ingratitude and Perjury to my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>It's groſs Injuſtice to my Parents.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7. <hi>It's an Affront to all the Godly.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8. <hi>It's ſelf-killing Cruelty to my own Soul.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:154397:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Here are hard and dreadful Words to make up the defect of weak Arguments; for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen ſome Perſons want Arguments <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to perſwade into an Error, they do uſe ſome terrible Words and Ways to fright People thereinto.</p>
               <p>Pray, Sir, ſhew your Hearers where you have Divine Authority for your Aſſertions, or elſe there is no ground to be concerned at all about it, though laid down in a formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable way. Though I know 'tis the Duty of Parents to pray for their Children, give them moderate Correction, good Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and good Examples; yet God never made it the Duty of any Parent to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate their Child in Baptiſm, nor the Duty of any Child to Engage and Covenant with God in their Infant-State, being altogether uncapable; therefore the not heeding it, cannot be any Sin, much leſs a damning Sin: and if ſo be Perſons do then ingage againſt the Cuſtom of this World, as you ſay they do, then they muſt engage againſt Infant-Baptiſm, being a worldly Cuſtom.</p>
               <p>I ſhall ſpeak briefly to all theſe Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Not to agree, or to refuſe to agree to the Covenant made in Infant-Baptiſm, is no Sin, becauſe, <hi>Where there is no Law,</hi> ſaith
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:154397:69"/> the Apoſtle <hi>John, there is no Tranſgreſſion.</hi> Now if this Gentleman can ſhew us any Law of God for Parents to dedicat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their Children in Baptiſm, or Children to cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with God in Baptiſm, I will give him the Cauſe; but if this cannot be done, I think he can do no leſs than make a publick Recantation of his Aſſertions, to unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thoſe whom he in ignorant Zeal may have deceived.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It's no Rebellion againſt our Maker; becauſe Rebellion is interpreted in the holy Writ, to be a wilful breach of God's Law and Command; as you may ſee in <hi>Numb.</hi> 20.24. <hi>Ye rebelled against my Word,</hi> Chap. 27.14. <hi>Ye rebelled against the Command of the Lord;</hi> ſo <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.26. Now then let this ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be more called Rebellion, except it can be proved to be againſt the Command of the Lord.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It can be no Ingratitude nor Perjury to my Redeemer. 1. No Ingratitude, becauſe to own a thing he never appointed, and is the ready way to thruſt out his own Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, will never be accounted by Chriſt Ingratitude. 2. Neither can it be Perjury. Mr. <hi>Pool</hi> on 1 Tim. 1. ſaith, <hi>Perjury, is a falſe Swearing, or ſwearing to an untrue thing.</hi>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:154397:69"/> Now I ſuppoſe this is not Mr. <hi>Williams</hi>'s meaning by Perjury; for the Propoſitions were true, if any, which were promiſed in Infant-Baptiſm: But I ſuppoſe he means the Covenant the Child made in Baptiſm, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt being governed by Satan and the Fleſh, taking up this World's Goods as my Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and againſt the Cuſtoms of the Men of the World as my Guide, when grown up, and found walking in the Ways of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, the Fleſh, and the World, contrary to God's Command and his own Vow: This I ſupoſe he calls Perjury to the Redeemer. But let it be conſidered, a Man muſt firſt make a Vow, or take an Oath, before he can be ſaid to break it, and be perjur'd. Now if the Child never made any Vow or Covenant in Baptiſm, it being impoſſible, how then can he be ſaid to break Covenant, and be guilty of Perjury to his Redeemer?</p>
               <p n="4">4. It cannot be Injuſtice, much leſs groſs Injuſtice to my Parents: becauſe what is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Injuſtice to my Parents, the Word of God makes it appear to be ſo ſome-where or other: but the Word of God doth not any where call that Child an unjuſt Child, that doth not own its dedicating by its Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in Baptiſm, or that they made any Covenant with God then.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:154397:70"/>5. It cannot be an Affront to all the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; becauſe there are thouſands that deny the thing; and I am bold to ſay it, were the Holy Apoſtles alive now, they would not have been affronted for any to deny their Parents dedicating Children in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, or Children denying they made any Covenant then, becauſe it's a thing God never revealed.</p>
               <p n="6">6. It cannot be a rejecting of Chriſt, as he ſaith; becauſe there are thouſands which own Chriſt, and accept him for King, Prieſt and Prophet, who deny Infants Baptiſm, and look upon it as nothing but an Invention of Men. And it's very ſevere to ſay, that thoſe many thouſands who now deny and diſown their Parents baptizing them in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, that they do reject Chriſt their Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, or the Bleſſings of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="7">7. It cannot be a Self-killing Cruelty to my own Soul, nor a damning Sin, not to agree to, or refuſe the Covenant made in Infant-Baptiſm, though I do not refuſe to be the Lord's, and in ſincerity care to know, love, believe, obey, and worſhip him, and ſerve him all my Days, and depend upon him, through Chriſt, for all Happineſs; yet this I do not, becauſe my Parents or Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:154397:70"/> did covenant or promiſe I ſhould do it, nor becauſe I my ſelf made any ſuch Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in my Infancy, for as much as it is all unſcriptural, and without a Divine Rule, therefore cannot be Self-killing, nor Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to my own Soul, nor a damning Sin, as this Gentleman ſaith: for the damning Sin is, final Impenitence and Unbelief; <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. <hi>He that believeth not, ſhall be damned.</hi> Perſons may believe the Covenant God hath made, and be ſaved; and though they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the Covenant in Infant-Baptiſm, they cannot be damned. I do not believe in time in Chriſt, becauſe either I my ſelf did in Infancy covenant ſo to do, or becauſe my Parents or Sureties covenanted for me; but I deny it, becauſe an human Invention.</p>
               <p>Yet I believe and obey from more ſolid Conſiderations.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) Becauſe I am commanded to it by God, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.23.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Becauſe his great Love conſtrains me, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) Becauſe of thoſe glorious Promiſes made to believing and obedient Souls, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17, 18. Chap. 7.1.</p>
               <p n="4">(4.) I am obliged unto it from the Law of Creation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.6.</p>
               <p n="5">(5.) Without Faith and Obedience I am in danger of loſing my Soul.</p>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:154397:71"/>
               <p>Therefore for Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> to tell the World, <hi>It is a damning Sin, not to agree to, or refuſe the Covenant made in Infancy,</hi> is a new Doctrine, which hath no footing in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erring Rule of the Word of God.</p>
               <p>If you will ſee the <hi>damning Sin,</hi> read Mr. <hi>Pool</hi>'s <hi>Synopſis,</hi> on <hi>John</hi> 3.18. <hi>He that believes not the Doctrine of Chriſt, and doth not, upon the Terms of the Goſpel, receive him for his Saviour, is already condemned for his obſtinate Infidelity, which is the certain Cauſe of Damnation.</hi> And further, <hi>The not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving in the only Son of God, who is able to ſave to the utmoſt all that regularly truſt in him, is ſuch a contempt of the merciful, alſufficient, ſole Means of Salvation, that 'tis abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and most juſt, that all thoſe who refuſe to be ſaved by him, ſhould periſh by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus you ſee what the <hi>damning Sin</hi> is. Therefore Mr. <hi>Williams</hi>'s Goſpel and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is to be looked upon as New in this Thing, and not agreeing to the old Goſpel, to aſſert, That <hi>it is a damning Sin, the Heart of all Sin, a rejecting Christ our Saviour, a renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Bleſſings of the Goſpel, Rebellion against my Maker, Ingratitude and Perjury to my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, groſs Injuſtice to my Parents, an Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front to all the Godly, and a ſelf-killing Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty to my own Soul, not to agree, or refuſe to
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:154397:71"/> agree to that Covenant made in Baptiſm in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy;</hi> though there be not one word in all the Holy Scripture to warrant that Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice or Principle.</p>
               <p n="8">8. If refuſing to agree to the Covenant to which my Baby-Baptiſm engaged me, be the Heart of all Sin; then I for my part, and many thouſands more, muſt be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all Sin; for it <hi>is the Heart of all Sin,</hi> ſaith this Gentleman. For my own part I do profeſs, that I do not obſerve any Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Duty, neither believe nor repent, by virtue of any Covenant my Parents made, or was made by my ſelf in my Baby-Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, becauſe God did never require ſuch a Covenant of my Parents, nor of my Self, who was wholly uncapable of ſuch a thing in Infancy.</p>
               <p>But the Reaſon why I deſire to obſerve the Terms of the Goſpel, is, becauſe it's God's Requirements and Command, <hi>That we believe on the Name of the only begotten Son of God,</hi> 1 John 3.23. And ſince I believed, I have made that Covenant with God in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, which you ſay, <hi>pag.</hi> 131. <hi>was made in Infancy,</hi> which I never remember, nor can I believe it is true, <hi>viz.</hi> I have <hi>engaged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt being governed by Satan or the Fleſh as my Rulers, and againſt taking up this World's Goods as my Portion, and againſt
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:154397:72"/> the Cuſtoms of the Men of the World as my Guide;</hi> therefore I reject that Baptiſm, becauſe a Cuſtom of the World. Now ſhould I refuſe to agree to this Covenant which I made after I believed, then I were a great Sinner indeed, becauſe one of my own making: But if I keep this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, tho I refuſe to agree to that Covenant made in my Infant-Baptiſm, <hi>I am a great Sinner,</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Williams) for it's the Heart of all Sin.</hi> If the Heart of all Sin, then of Murder, Adultery, Sabbath-breaking, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt, Hereſy, Drunkenneſs, Idolatry, Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery, Lying, Covetouſneſs, Railing, Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, Buggery, Extortion, Envy, Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, Contention, Gluttony, Rebellion, Perjury, Ingratitude, Injuſtice, an Affront to the Godly, Self-killing; <hi>In a word,</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>Williams, it's a damning Sin.</hi> Now it's high time for the poor Baptiſts to cry, <hi>Lord, have Mercy upon us,</hi> for this Gentleman damns us all at once. But this is our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, he ſhall not be our Judg, nor that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine he hath delivered, but both he and we muſt be tried by another Goſpel, and another Doctrine than he preacheth upon this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
               <p>And whereas he calls Baptiſm in Infancy, <hi>a Seal of the Covenant,</hi> pag. 130. Pray, Sir, what did it ſeal to the Infant then? did it
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:154397:72"/> ſeal the Love of God, pardon of Sin, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation or Adoption, Juſtification or Remiſſion? If ſo, as you grant, by referring to <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39 then, Sir, if they are juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and their Sins remitted, then <hi>they must be glorified,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30. <hi>Whom he justified, them he glorified.</hi> I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you may be for final Perſeverance: if ſo, then not an Infant of theſe can miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry.</p>
               <p>But if you ſay theſe things may be ſealed in Infancy, and yet be never enjoyed for want of actual Faith. How then! is a Perſon par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, and not pardoned; juſtified, and not justified; in Covenant, and not in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant? theſe are Contradictions with a witneſs. What! is the Covenant ſealed, and nothing in the Covenant enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? doth God ſeal to a Blank? Men are more wiſe than ſo to do; for there is always ſomething antecedent to the Seal. When a Covenant is ſealed among Men, ſomething is ſealed unto them; ſo when God ſeals, 'tis not to a Blank, but it's his Covenant of Grace ſealed: <hi>After you believed, you were ſealed with the Holy Spirit of Promiſe,</hi> Epheſ. 1.13. Mark, 'tis not before they believed, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they believed they were ſealed. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Infant-Baptiſm is no Seal of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, for they do not believe. But
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:154397:73"/> after Perſons believe, then the Sacraments of Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper are Seals of the Covenant of Grace, but not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p>And whereas Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> aſſerts, <hi>pag.</hi> 130. <hi>Believers and their Infant-Seed are in the Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We reply; This Word <hi>Covenant</hi> is an unintelligible word, for not one in an Hundred, if one in a Thouſand, knows what is meant by it.</p>
               <p>I know but two ways of being in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, either Abſolutely, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionally.</p>
               <p n="1">1. No Believers dare ſay, all their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are Abſolutely in the Covenant of Grace, becauſe there is no falling away from it: But behold, how many of God's People have their Children die, of whom they have little hope?</p>
               <p>Or, 2. they are in the Covenant of Grace conditionally; that is to ſay, <hi>If they repent, and believe.</hi> Upon this Condition, and on theſe Terms, the Children of Unbelievers are in the Covenant of Grace alſo, and have the ſame right to the Seals of the Covenant as the Children of Believers have; and there are none to have the Seals, or Signs of the Covenant, but thoſe whom God hath
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:154397:73"/> ordained and appointed ſhould have them, which are thoſe who repent, and actually believe. For, mark, though <hi>Lot</hi> was a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Man, yet he had no ſuch priviledg to Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe his Infant-Seed, becauſe it was li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited unto <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed; and the Male Sex, and the eighth Day, appointed by a ſpecial Command. Even ſo, Baptiſm is limited by a ſpecial Command of God to Actual Believers.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PReface,</hi> Page 3. line 3, 4. read, <hi>two or three hours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>In the Book.</label> PAg. 35. Marg. r. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. P. 41. l. 14. r. <hi>fit or unfit.</hi> P. 55. Marg. l. 6. for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> r. <hi>John.</hi> P. 69. l. 4. r. <hi>Church of Rome.</hi> P. 90. Col. 1. l. 1. f. <hi>Perſons,</hi> r. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers.</hi> P. 95. l. 15. r. <hi>Biſhop of Munſter.</hi> P. 100. l. 2. f. <hi>bave,</hi> r. <hi>bad.</hi> P. 118. l. 25, 26. r. <hi>the word Baptiſt.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
